<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!-- Compiles with XML2RFC v3 https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/cgi-bin/xml2rfc-dev.cgi -->

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-raw-architecture-17"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF"
     xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RAW Architecture">Reliable and Available Wireless
    Architecture</title>

   <author initials='P' surname='Thubert' fullname='Pascal Thubert' role='editor'>
      <!-- <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization> -->
      <address>
         <postal>
            <city>Roquefort-les-Pins</city>
            <code>06330</code>
          <country>France</country>
         </postal>
         <email>pascal.thubert@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>


    <date/>
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>RAW</workgroup>
    <keyword>Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>

      Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) provides for high reliability and
      availability for IP connectivity across any combination of wired and
      wireless network segments.

      The RAW Architecture extends the DetNet Architecture and other
      standard IETF concepts and mechanisms to adapt to the specific challenges
      of the wireless medium, in particular intermittently lossy connectivity.

      This document defines a network control loop that optimizes the use of
      constrained spectrum and energy while maintaining the expected
      connectivity properties, typically reliability and latency.

      The loop involves DetNet Operational Plane functions, with a new recovery
      Function and a new Point of Local Repair operation, that dynamically
      selects the DetNet path(s) for the future packets
      to route around local degradations and failures.

      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>
   Deterministic Networking is an attempt to emulate the properties of a serial
   link over a switched fabric, by providing a bounded latency and eliminating
   congestion loss, even when co-existing with best-effort traffic.
   It is getting traction in various industries including professional A/V,
   manufacturing, online gaming, and smartgrid automation, with both cost
   savings and complexity benefits (e.g., vs. loads of P2P cables).
      </t>
      <t>
   Bringing determinism in a packet network means eliminating the statistical
   effects of multiplexing that result in probabilistic jitter and loss.
   This can be approached with a tight control of the physical resources to
   maintain the amount of traffic within a budgeted volume of data per unit of
   time that fits the physical capabilities of the underlying network, and
   the use of time-shared resources (bandwidth and buffers) per circuit, and/or
   by shaping and/or scheduling the packets at every hop.
   </t>
   <t>
   This innovation was initially introduced on wired networks, with IEEE 802.1
   Time Sensitive networking (TSN) - for Ethernet LANs - and IETF DetNet.
   But the wired and the wireless media are fundamentally different at the
   physical level and in the possible abstractions that can be built for IPv6
   <xref target="RFC8200"/>, more in
   <xref target="I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless" format="default"/>.
   Nevertheless, deterministic capabilities are required in a number of wireless
   use cases as well <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases"/>. With new scheduled
   radios such as TSCH and OFDMA <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"/>
   being developed to provide determinism over wireless links at the lower
   layers, providing DetNet capabilities is now becoming possible.
   </t>
   <t>
   Wireless networks operate on a shared medium where uncontrolled interference,
   including the self-induced multipath fading cause random transmission losses.
   Fixed and mobile obstacles and reflectors may block or alter the signal,
   causing transient and unpredictable variations of the throughput and packet
   delivery ratio (PDR) of a wireless link. This adds new dimensions to the
   statistical effects that affect the quality and reliability of the link.
   </t><t>
   Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) takes up the challenge of providing
   highly available and reliable end-to-end performances in a network with
   scheduled wireless segments. To achieve this, RAW leverages multiple links
   and parallel transmissions, providing enough diversity and redundancy to
   ensure the timely packet delivery while preserving energy and optimizing the
   use of the shared spectrum.
   </t>
   <t>
    As opposed to routing trees, Distance-Vector protocols can enable more than
    one feasible successors along non-equal-cost multipath forwarding graphs.
    This provide redundancy and allow to dynamically adapt the forwarding
    operation to the state of the links. But this protection is limited since
    only a subset of the nodes along the path will have an alternate feasible
    successor.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW solves that problem by defining Protection Paths that can be fully
    non-congruent and can be activated dynamically upon failures. This requires
    additional control to take the routing decision early enough along the
    possible paths to route around the failure. RAW defines a end-to-end
    control loop that dynamically controls the activation and deactivation of
    the feasible Protection Paths.
    </t>
    <t>
	In addition, RAW introduces the RAW API, which is an interface between the
	lower layer wireless technology and the DetNet layers. The RAW API is RAW 
	technology <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"/> dependent as it can
	vary what the different RAW technologies expose towards the DetNet layers. 
	Furthermore, the different RAW technologies are equipped with different 
	reliability features, e.g., short range broadcast, MUMIMO, PHY rate and 
	other Modulation Coding Scheme (MCS) adaptation, (H)ARQ, constructive 
	interference and overhearing. The RAW API enables interactions between the
	reliability functions provided by the wireless technology and the 
	reliability functions provided by DetNet. That is, the RAW API makes 
	cross-layer optimization possible for the reliability functions of 
	different layers depending on the actual exposure provided via the RAW API
	by the given RAW technology.
    </t>
   <t>This document presents the RAW problem and associated terminology in
   <xref target="problem"/>, presents a conceptual model for RAW in
   <xref target="model"/>, and, based on that model, elaborates on an
   in-network optimization control loop in <xref target="ooda"/>.
   </t>
    </section>
    <!-- Introduction -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->


   <section anchor="terms" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>Terminology</name>

    <t>RAW reuses terminology defined for DetNet in the <xref target="RFC8655">
    "Deterministic Networking Architecture"</xref>, e.g., PREOF for Packet
    Replication, Elimination and Ordering Functions. RAW inherits and augments
    the IETF art of Protection as seen in DetNet and Traffic Engineering.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW also reuses terminology defined for MPLS in <xref target=
    "RFC4427" format="default"/> such as the term recovery as covering
    both Protection and Restoration, a number of recovery types,
    That document defines a number of concepts like recovery domain that are
    used in the RAW works, and creates the new term recovery graph.
    A recovery graph associates a topological graph with usage metadata that
    represent how the paths within the recovery graph are built.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW also reuses terminology defined for RSVP-TE in <xref target=
    "RFC4090" format="default"/> such as the Point of Local Repair (PLR).
    The concept of backup path is generalized with protection path, which is the
    term mostly found in recent standards and used in this document.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW also reuses terminology defined for 6TiSCH in <xref target=
    "RFC9030" format="default"/> and equates the concept of recovery graph with that of a
    recovery graph.
    </t>
    <t>In an quantic analogy, a recovery graph is to a path what an atomic orbital is to
    a planetary orbit, in that the electron has a probability of presence within
    a known shape as opposed to a deterministic trajectory.
    </t>
    <t>
    The concept of recovery graph is agnostic to
    the underlaying technology and applies but is not limited to any fully or
    partially wireless mesh.
    RAW specifies strict and loose recovery graphs depending on whether the path is fully
    controlled by RAW or traverses an opaque network where RAW cannot observe
    and control the individual hops.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW uses the following terminology and acronyms:
    </t>

    <section><name>Acronyms</name>
    <section><name>ARQ</name>
    <t>
	Automatic Repeat Request, a well-known mechanism, enabling an acknowledged
	transmission with retries to mitigate errors and loss. ARQ may be 
	implemented at various layers in a network. ARQ is typically implemented at
	Layer-2, per hop and not end-to-end in wireless networks. ARQ improves 
	delivery on lossy wireless. Additionally, ARQ retransmission may be further
	limited by a bounded time to meet end-to-end packet latency constraints. 
	Additional details and considerations for ARQ are detailed in 
	<xref target="RFC3366"/>.	
    </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>FEC</name>
    <t>
    Forward Error Correction, adding redundant data to protect against a partial
    loss without retries.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>HARQ</name>
    <t>
    Hybrid Automatic Repeat Request, combining FEC and ARQ.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>MCS</name>
    <t>
    Modulation and Coding Scheme. Controls the throughput of the Link to
    maintain reliable transmissions.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>OAM</name>
    <t>
      OAM stands for Operations, Administration, and Maintenance, and
      covers the processes, activities, tools, and standards involved
      with operating, administering, managing and maintaining any
      system.  This document uses the terms Operations, Administration,
      and Maintenance, in conformance with the <xref target="RFC6291">
      'Guidelines for the Use of the "OAM" Acronym in the IETF'</xref>
      and the system observed by the RAW OAM is the recovery graph.

     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>OODA</name>
    <t>
    Observe, Orient, Decide, Act. The OODA Loop is a
    conceptual cyclic model developed by USAF Colonel John Boyd, and that is
    applicable in multiple domains where agility can provide benefits against
    brute force.
    </t>
    </section>
    </section><!--Acronyms-->

    <section><name>Link and Direction</name>

    <section><name>Flapping</name>
    <t>
    In the context of RAW, a link flaps when the reliability of the wireless
    connectivity drops abruptly for a short period of time, typically of a
    subsecond to seconds duration.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Uplink</name>
    <t>
     Connection from end-devices to a data communication equipment. In the
     context of wireless, uplink refers to the connection between a station
     (STA) and a controller (AP) or a User Equipment (UE) to a Base Station (BS)
     such as a 3GPP 5G gNodeB (gNb).
     </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Downlink</name>
    <t>
      The reverse direction from uplink.
     </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Downstream</name>
    <t>
     Following the direction of the flow data path along a recovery graph.
     </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Upstream</name>
    <t>
     Against the direction of the flow data path along a recovery graph.
     </t>
     </section>

    </section><!-- Link and Direction -->


    <section anchor="pt"><name>Path and Recovery Graphs</name>
    <section><name>Path</name>

    <t>
    Quoting section 1.1.3 of <xref target="RFC1122"/>:
    </t>
    <blockquote>
    At a given moment, all the IP datagrams from a particular source host to a
    particular destination host will typically traverse the same sequence of
    gateways.  We use the term "path" for this sequence.  Note that a path is
    unidirectional; it is not unusual to have different paths in the two
    directions between a given host pair.
    </blockquote>
    <t>
    Section 2 of <xref target="I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties"/> points to a
    longer, more modern definition of path, which begins as follows:
    </t>
    <blockquote>
    A sequence of adjacent path elements over which a packet can
    be transmitted, starting and ending with a node.  A path is
    unidirectional.  Paths are time-dependent, i.e., the sequence of
    path elements over which packets are sent from one node to another
    may change.  A path is defined between two nodes.
    </blockquote>
    <t>
    It follows that the general acceptance of a path is a linear sequence of
    links and nodes, as opposed to a multi-dimensional graph, defined by the
    experience of the packet that went from a node A to a node B.
    In the context of this document, a path is observed by following one copy
    or one fragment of a packet that conserves its uniqueness and integrity.
    For instance, if C replicates to E and F and D eliminates on the way from A
    to B, a packet from A to B experiences 2 paths, A->C->E->D->B and
    A->C->F->D->B. The terms lane is used to clarify when
    dealing with such path.
    </t>
    <t> With DetNet and RAW,
    a packet may be duplicated, fragmented and network-coded, and the various
    byproducts may travel different paths that are not necessarily end-to-end
    between A and B; we refer to that complex experience as a DetNet path.
    As such, the DetNet path extends the above description of a path,
    but it still matches the experience of a packet that traverses the network.
    </t>
    <t>
    With RAW, that experience is subject to change from a packet to the next,
    but all the possible experiences are all contained within a finite set.
    Therefore, we introduce below the term of a recovery graph that coalesces
    that set and covers the overall topology where the possible DetNet paths are
    all contained. As such, the recovery graph coalesces all the possible paths
    a flow
    may experience, each with its own statistical probability to be used.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="trk"><name>Recovery Graph</name>

    <t>A networking graph that can be followed to transport packets with
    equivalent treatment, associated with usage metadata; as opposed to the
    definition of a path above, a recovery graph represents not an actual but a
    potential, it is not necessarily a linear sequence like a simple path, and
    is not
    necessarily fully traversed (flooded) by all packets of a flow like a Detnet
    Path. Still, and as a simplification, the casual reader may consider that a
    recovery graph is very much like a DetNet path, aggregating multiple paths that may
    overlap, fork and rejoin, for instance to enable a protection service by the
    PREOF operations.
    </t>
   <figure anchor="Figtrk">
          <name>Example IoT Recovery Graph to an IoT Gateway with 1+1 Redundancy</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
       <![CDATA[
             +---------+
             | IoT G/W |
             +---------+
                 EGR  <=== Elimination at Egress
                 | |
         /------/   \-------\    Wired backbone
         |                  |
      +--|--+            +--|--+
      |  |  | Backbone   |  |  | Backbone
      |  |  | Router     |  |  | Router
      +--|--+            +--|--+
         |                  |
      o   \     o          /  lane
    o      o      o---o---o   o      o   o  o
            \  o /    o          o         o
     o   o   \  /       o        low power lossy network
              \/ o           o        o
           o  IN <=== Replication at recovery graph Ingress
               |
               o <- source device
    ]]>
       </artwork>
       </figure>

    <t>
    Refining further, a recovery graph is defined as the coalescence of the collection
    of all the feasible DetNet Paths that a packet which flow is assigned to the
    recovery graph may be forwarded along.
    A packet that is assigned to the recovery graph will experience one of the feasible
    DetNet Paths based on the current selection by the PLR at the time the
    packet traverses the network.
    </t>
    <t>
    Refining even further, the feasible DetNet Paths within the recovery graph may or may
    not be computed in advance, but decided upon the detection of a change from
    a clean slate.
    Furthermore, the PLR decision may be distributed, which yields a large
    combination of possible and dependant decisions, with no node in the network
    capable of reporting which is the current DetNet Path within the recovery graph.
    </t>
    <t>
    In DetNet <xref target="RFC8655"/> terms, a recovery graph has the following
    properties:
    </t>
    <ul>
    <li>
    A recovery graph is a Layer-3 abstraction built upon P2P IP links between routers.
    A router may form multiple P2P IP links over a single radio interface.
    </li><li>
    A recovery graph has one Ingress and one Egress nodes, which operate as DetNet Edge
    nodes.
    </li><li>
    The graph of a recovery graph is reversible, meaning that packets can be routed against
    the flow of data packets, e.g., to carry OAM measurements or control
    messages back to the Ingress.
    </li><li>
    The vertices of that graph are DetNet Relay nodes that operate at the
    DetNet Service sub-layer and provide the PREOF functions.
    </li><li>
    The topological edges of the graph are strict sequences of DetNet Transit
    nodes that operate at the DetNet Forwarding sub-layer.
    </li>
    </ul>




    <t>
    <xref target='TRK'/> illustrates the generic concept of a recovery graph,
   between an Ingress Node and an Egress Node

    The recovery graph is composed of forward Lanes and forward or crossing
    Segments, see the definition for those terms in the next sections.
    A Protection Path contains at least 2 Lanes as a main path and a backup path.
</t>
<figure anchor='TRK'><name>A Recovery Graph and its Components</name>
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

 ------------------- forward direction ---------------------->

       a ==> b ==> C -=- F ==> G ==> H     T1       I: Ingress
     /              \   /      |       \ /          E: Egress
   I                  o        n        E -=- T2    T1, T2, T3:
     \              /   \      |       / \            External
       p ==> q ==> R -=- T ==> U ==> v     T3         Targets

      Uppercase: DetNet Relay nodes
      Lowercase: DetNet Transit nodes

      I ==> a ==> b ==> C : an forward Segment to targets F and o
      C ==> o ==> T: an forward Segment to target T (and/or U)
      G | n | U : a crossing Segment to targets G or U
      I --> F --> E : an forward Lane to targets T1, T2, and T3

      I, a, b, C, F, G, H, E : a path to T1, T2, and/or T3
      I, p, q, R, o, F, G, H, E : lane-crossing alternate path

]]></artwork>
</figure>


    </section>
  <section><name>Forward and Crossing</name>
    <t>
    Forward refers to progress towards the recovery graph Egress. Forward links are
    directional, and packets that are forwarded along the recovery graph can only be
    transmitted along the link direction. Crossing links are bidirectional,
    meaning that they can be used in both directions, though a given packet may
    use the link in one direction only. A Segment can be forward, in which
    case it is composed of forward links only, or crossing, in which
    case it is composed of crossing links only. A lane is always forward,
    meaning that is is composed of forward links and Segments.
    </t>
    </section>
  <section><name>Lane</name>
    <t>
    An end-to-end forward lane between the Ingress and Egress Nodes of a
    recovery graph. A lane in a recovery graph is expressed as a strict sequence
    of DetNet Relay nodes or as a loose sequence of DetNet Relay nodes that are
    joined by recovery graph Segments.
    </t>
  </section>
    <section><name>Segment</name>
    <t>
    A strict sequence of DetNet Transit nodes between 2 DetNet Relay nodes; a
    Segment of a recovery graph is composed topologically of two vertices of the
    recovery graph and one edge of the recovery graph between those vertices.
    </t>
    </section>

    </section><!--Path and recovery graphs-->


    <section><name>Deterministic Networking</name>
    <t>This document reuses the terminology in section 2 of
    <xref target="RFC8557"/> and section 4.1.2 of <xref target="RFC8655"/>
    for deterministic networking and deterministic networks.
    </t>
    <section><name>Flow</name>
    <t>
    A collection of consecutive IP packets defined by the upper layers and
    signaled by the same 5 or 6-tuple, see section 5.1 of
    <xref target="RFC8939"/>. Packets of the same flow must be placed
    on the same recovery graph to receive an equivalent treatment from Ingress to Egress
    within the recovery graph. Multiple flows may be transported along the same recovery graph.
    The DetNet Path that is selected for the flow may change over time under the
    control of the PLR.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Deterministic Flow Identifier (L2)</name>
    <t>
     A tuple identified by a stream_handle, and provided by a bridge, in
     accordance with IEEE 802.1CB.
     The tuple comprises at least source MAC, destination MAC, VLAN ID, and L2 priority.
     Continuous streams are characterized by bandwidth and max packet size;
     scheduled streams are characterized by a repeating pattern of timed
     transmissions.
     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Deterministic Flow Identifier (L3)</name>
    <t>
     See section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC8938"/>. The classical IP 5-tuple that
     identifies a flow comprises the source IP, destination IP, source port,
     destination port, and
     the upper layer protocol (ULP). DetNet uses a 6-tuple where the extra field
     is the DSCP field in the packet. The IPv6 flow label is not used for that
     purpose.
     </t>
     </section>
     <section><name>TSN</name>
    <t>
    TSN stands for Time Sensitive Networking and denotes the efforts at IEEE
    802 for deterministic networking, originally for use on Ethernet. Wireless
    TSN (WTSN) denotes extensions of the TSN work on wireless media such as
    the selected RAW technologies <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"/>.
    </t>
    </section>
     </section><!--Deterministic Networking -->


    <section><name>Reliability and Availability</name>
    <t>
    In the context of the RAW work, Reliability and Availability are defined as
    follows:
    </t>

    <section><name>Service Level Agreement</name>
    <t>
    In the context of RAW, an SLA (service level agreement) is a contract
    between a provider, the network, and a client, the application flow,
    about measurable metrics such as latency boundaries, consecutive losses,
    and packet delivery ratio (PDR).
    </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Service Level Objective</name>
    <t>
    A service level objective (SLO) is one term in the SLA, for which specific
    network setting and operations are implemented. For instance, a dynamic
    tuning of the packet redundancy will address an SLO of consecutive losses in
    a row by augmenting the chances of delivery of a packet that follows a loss.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Service Level Indicator</name>
    <t>
    A service level indicator (SLI) measures the compliance of an SLO to the
    terms of the contract. It can be for instance the statistics of individual
    losses and losses in a row as time series.).
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Reliability</name>
    <t>
    Reliability is a measure of the probability that an item will perform its
    intended function for a specified interval under stated conditions (SLA).
    RAW expresses reliability in terms of Mean Time Between Failure (MTBF)
    and Maximum Consecutive Failures (MCF). More in <xref target="NASA"/>.).
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Available</name>
    <t>
    That is exempt of unscheduled outage or derivation from the terms of the SLA.
    A basic expectation for a RAW network is that the flow is maintained in the
    face of any single breakage or flapping.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Availability</name>
    <t>
    Availability is a measure of the relative amount of time where a RAW Network
    operates in stated condition (SLA), expressed as (uptime)/(uptime+downtime).
    Because a wireless lane may not be good enough to provide the
    required reliability, and even 2 parallel lanes may not be over a longer
    period of time, the RAW availability implies a journey that is a lot more
    complex than following a serial path.
    </t>
    </section>

    </section><!--Reliability and Availability-->

    <section><name>OAM variations</name>
    <section><name>Active OAM</name>
    <t>
     See <xref target="RFC7799"/>. In the context of RAW, Active OAM is used to
     observe a particular recovery graph, DetNet Path, or Segment of a recovery graph regardless of
     whether it is used for traffic at that time.
     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>In-Band OAM</name>
    <t>
     An active OAM packet is considered in-band for the
      monitored recovery graph when it traverses the same set of links and interfaces
      and if the OAM packet receives the same QoS and service protection treatment as the
      packets of the data flows that are injected in the recovery graph.
     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Out-of-Band OAM</name>
    <t>
     Out-of-band OAM is an active OAM whose path is not topologically congruent
     to the recovery graph, or its test packets receive a
      QoS and/or service protection treatment that is different from that of the packets of
      the data flows that are injected in the recovery graph, or both.
     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Limited OAM</name>
    <t>
     An active OAM packet is a Limited OAM packet when
      it observes the RAW operation over a node, a segment, or a DetNet Path
      of the recovery graph, though not from Ingress to Egress.  It is injected
      in the datapath and extracted from the datapath around the
      particular function or subnetwork (e.g., around a relay providing
      a Service sub-layer replication point) that is being tested.
     </t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Upstream OAM</name>

     <t>
    An upstream OAM packet is an Out-of-Band OAM packet that traverses the recovery graph
    from egress to ingress on the reverse direction, to capture and  report OAM
    measurements upstream. The collection may capture all information along the
    whole recovery graph, or it may only learn select data across all, or only a
    particular DetNet Path, or Segment of a recovery graph.
     </t>
</section> <!-- Upstream OAM -->

    <section><name>Residence Time</name>
    <t>
    A residence time (RT) is defined as the
    time period between the reception of a packet starts and the
    transmission of the packet begins. In the context of RAW, RT is useful
    for a transit node, not ingress or egress.
    </t>
    </section>


    <section><name>Lower Layer information</name>
    <t>
    The RAW Operational Plane elements (PLR and OAM Supervisor) may gather
    aggregated information from lower layers about e.g., link quality.
    This information may be obtained from inside the device using
    specialized API (e.g., L2 triggers) or via control protocols such as BFD
    <xref target="RFC5880"/> or DLEP <xref target="RFC8175"/>. It may then be
    massaged and exported through oOAM messaging, and passed to the Controller
    Plane using the aCPF.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section><name>Additional References</name>
    <t>  <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework" format="default"/>
    provides additional terminology related to OAM in the context of DetNet and
    by extension of RAW, whereas <xref target="RFC7799"/> defines the Active,
    Passive, and Hybrid OAM methods.
    </t>
</section> <!-- Additional References -->

</section> <!-- OAM variations -->


    </section><!-- Terminology -->
    <!--  1111111111111111    -->
    <section anchor="raw" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliable and Available Wireless</name>


    <!--  111  -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliability and Availability</name>


    <!--  2222222222222222    -->
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>High Availability Engineering Principles</name>

    <t>
    The reliability criteria of a critical system pervades through its elements,
    and if the system comprises a data network then the data network is also
    subject to the inherited reliability and availability criteria.
    It is only natural to consider the art of high availability engineering and
    apply it to wireless communications in the context of RAW.
    </t>

    <t>
    There are three principles [pillars] of high availability engineering:
    </t>
     <ol spacing="compact">
     <li>elimination of single points of failure</li>
     <li>reliable crossover</li>
     <li>prompt detection of failures as they occur.</li>
     </ol>
     <t>
     These principles are common to all high availability systems, not just ones
     with Internet technology at the center.  Examples of both non-Internet and
     Internet are included.
    </t>


    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Elimination of Single Points of Failure</name>

    <t>
    Physical and logical components in a system happen to fail, either as the
    effect of wear and tear, when used beyond acceptable limits, or due to a
    software bug.
    It is necessary to decouple component failure from system failure to avoid
    the latter.
    This allows failed components to be restored while the rest of the system
    continues to function.
    </t>
    <t>
    IP Routers leverage routing protocols to compute alternate routes in case
    of a failure. There is a rather open-ended issue over alternate routes --
    for example, when links are cabled through the same conduit, they form a
    shared risk link group (SRLG), and will share the same fate if the bundle is
    cut. The same effect can happen with virtual links that end up in a same
    physical transport through the games of encapsulation. In a same fashion,
    an interferer or an obstacle may affect multiple wireless transmissions at
    the same time, even between different sets of peers.
    </t>
    <t>
    Intermediate network Nodes such as routers, switches and APs, wire bundles
    and the air medium itself can become single points of failure. For High
    Availability, it is thus required to use physically link- and Node-disjoint
    paths; in the wireless space, it is also required to use the highest
    possible degree of diversity (time, space, code, frequency, channel width)
    in the transmissions over the air to combat the additional causes of
    transmission loss.
    </t>
    <t>
    From an economics standpoint, executing this principle properly generally
    increases capitalization expense because of the redundant equipment. In a
    constrained network where the waste of energy and bandwidth should be
    minimized, an excessive use of redundant links must be avoided; for RAW this
    means that the extra bandwidth must be used wisely and with parsimony.
    </t>

    </section>
      <!--Elimination of Single Points of Failure-->



    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliable Crossover</name>

    <t>
    Having a backup equipment has a limited value unless it can be reliably
    switched into use within the down-time parameters.
    IP Routers execute reliable crossover continuously because
    the routers will use any alternate routes that are available <xref target=
    "RFC0791"/>. This is due to the stateless nature of IP datagrams and the
    dissociation of the datagrams from the forwarding routes they take.
    The <xref target="RFC5714">"IP Fast Reroute Framework"</xref> analyzes
    mechanisms for fast failure detection and path repair for IP Fast-Reroute,
    and discusses the case of multiple failures and SRLG. Examples of FRR
    techniques include Remote Loop-Free Alternate <xref target="RFC7490"/> and
    backup label-switched path (LSP) tunnels for the local repair of LSP tunnels
    using RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC4090"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
    Deterministic flows, on the contrary, are attached to specific paths where
    dedicated resources are reserved for each flow. Therefore each DetNet path
    must inherently provide sufficient redundancy to provide the guaranteed SLA
    at all times.
    The DetNet PREOF typically leverages 1+1 redundancy whereby a packet is sent
    twice, over non-congruent paths. This avoids the gap during the fast reroute
    operation, but doubles the traffic in the network.
    </t>
    <t>
    In the case of RAW, the expectation is that multiple transient faults may
    happen in overlapping time windows, in which case the 1+1 redundancy with
    delayed reestablishment of the second path will not provide the required
    guarantees.
    The Data Plane must be configured with a sufficient degree of
    redundancy to select an alternate redundant path immediately upon a fault,
    without the need for a slow intervention from the Controller Plane.
    </t>
    </section>
      <!--Reliable Crossover-->





    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Prompt Notification of Failures</name>
    <t>
    The execution of the two above principles is likely to render a system where
    the user will rarely see a failure. But someone needs to in order to direct
    maintenance.
    </t>
    <t>
    There are many reasons for system monitoring (FCAPS for fault, configuration,
    accounting, performance, security is a handy mental checklist) but fault
    monitoring is sufficient reason.
    </t>
    <t>
    <xref target="RFC3411">"An Architecture for Describing
    Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks"</xref>
    describes how to use SNMP to observe and correct long-term faults.
    </t>
    <t>
    <xref target="RFC3272">
    "Overview and Principles of Internet Traffic Engineering"</xref> discusses
    the importance of measurement for network protection, and provides abstract
    an method for network survivability with the analysis of a traffic matrix
    as observed by SNMP, probing techniques, FTP, IGP link state advertisements,
    and more.
    </t>

    <t>
    Those measurements are needed in the context of RAW to inform the controller
    and make the long term reactive decision to rebuild a recovery graph based on
    statistical and aggregated information. RAW itself operates in the DetNet
    Network
    Plane at a faster time scale with live information on speed, state, etc...
    This live information can be obtained directly from the lower layer, e.g.,
    using L2 triggers, read from a protocol such as the <xref target="RFC8175">
    Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP)</xref>, or transported over multiple
    hops using OAM and reverse OAM, as illustrated in <xref target="Figlearn"/>.
    </t>

<!--

    Security requirements. SNMP messages need to be authentic in all cases.
    Implementations may need to be confidential as well.



[ ... dovetail this into the OAM things that need to be included. Most of the discussion seems to cluster around performance management]

-->
    </section>
      <!--Prompt Notification of Failures-->




   </section>
      <!--Reliability Engineering-->
    <!--  22222222222222222222    -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Applying Reliability Concepts to Networking</name>
    <t>
    The terms Reliability and Availability are defined for use in RAW in
    <xref target="terms"/> and the reader is invited to read
    <xref target="NASA"/>
    for more details on the general definition of Reliability.
    Practically speaking a number of nines is often used to indicate the
    reliability of a data link, e.g., 5 nines indicate a
    Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR) of 99.999%.
    </t>
    <t>
    This number is typical in a wired
    environment where the loss is due to a random event such as a solar particle
    that affects the transmission of a particular frame, but does not affect the
    previous or next frame, nor frames transmitted on other links. Note that the
    QoS requirements in RAW may include a bounded latency, and a packet that
    arrives too late is a fault and not considered as delivered.
    </t>
    <t>
    For a periodic networking pattern such as an automation control loop, this
    number is proportional to the Mean Time Between Failures (MTBF).
    When a single fault can have dramatic consequences, the MTBF expresses the
    chances that the unwanted fault event occurs. In data networks,
    this is rarely the case. Packet loss cannot never be fully avoided and the
    systems are built to resist to one loss, e.g., using redundancy with Retries
    (HARQ) or Packet Replication and Elimination (PRE), or, in a typical control
    loop, by linear interpolation from the previous measurements.
    </t>
   <t>
    But the linear interpolation method cannot resist multiple consecutive
    losses, and a high MTBF is desired as a guarantee that this will not happen,
    IOW that the number of losses-in-a-row can be bounded. In that case, what is
    really desired is a Maximum Consecutive Failures (MCF).
    If the number of losses in a row passes the MCF, the control loop has to
    abort and the system, e.g., the production line, may need to enter an
    emergency stop condition.
    </t>
   <t>
    Engineers that build automated processes may use the network reliability
    expressed in nines or as an MTBF as a proxy to indicate an MCF, e.g., as
    described in section 7.4 of the <xref target="RFC8578">"Deterministic
    Networking Use Cases"</xref>.
    </t>
    </section>
      <!--Applying Reliability concepts to Networking-->
    <!--  22222222222222222222    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Wireless Effects Affecting Reliability</name>
    <t>
    In contrast with wired networks, errors in transmission are the predominant
    source of packet loss in wireless networks.
    </t>
    <t>
    The root cause for the loss may be of multiple origins, calling for
    the use of different forms of diversity:
    </t>
    <dl>
    <dt>Multipath Fading:</dt>
    <dd>
    <t>A destructive interference by a reflection of the original signal.
    </t>
    <t>A radio signal may be received directly
    (line-of-sight) and/or as a reflection on a physical structure (echo).
    The reflections take a longer path and are delayed by the extra distance
    divided by the speed of light in the medium. Depending on the frequency, the
    echo lands with a different phase which may add up to (constructive
    interference) or cancel the direct signal (destructive interference).
    </t>
    <t>
    The affected frequencies depend on the relative position of the sender, the
    receiver, and all the reflecting objects in the environment.
    A given hop will suffer from multipath fading for multiple packets in a
    row till a physical movement changes the reflection patterns.
    </t>
    </dd>
    <dt>Co-channel Interference:</dt>
    <dd>
    <t>
    Energy in the spectrum used for the transmission confuses the receiver.
    </t>
    <t>
    The wireless medium itself is a Shared Risk Link Group (SRLG) for nearby
    users of the same spectrum, as an interference may affect multiple co-channel
    transmissions between different peers within the interference domain of the
    interferer, possibly even when they use different technologies.
    </t>
    </dd>
    <dt>Obstacle in Fresnel Zone:</dt>
    <dd>

    <t>
    The optimal transmission happens when the Fresnel Zone between the sender
    and the receiver is free of obstacles.
    </t>
    <t>
    As long as a physical object (e.g., a metallic trolley between peers) that
    affects the transmission is not removed, the quality of the link is affected.
    </t>
    </dd>
    </dl>
    <t>
    In an environment that is rich of metallic structures and mobile objects, a
    single radio link will provide a fuzzy service, meaning that it cannot be trusted to transport the traffic reliably over a long period of time.
    </t>
    <t>
    Transmission losses are typically not independent, and their nature and
    duration are unpredictable; as long as a physical object (e.g., a metallic
    trolley between peers) that affects the transmission is not removed, or as
    long as the interferer (e.g., a radar) keeps transmitting, a continuous
    stream of packets will be affected.
    </t>
    <t>
    The key technique to combat those unpredictable losses is diversity.
    Different forms of diversity are necessary to combat different causes of
    loss and the use of diversity must be maximized to optimize the PDR.
    </t>
    <t>
    A single packet may be sent at different times (time diversity) over diverse
    paths (spatial diversity) that rely on diverse radio channels (frequency
    diversity) and diverse PHY technologies, e.g., narrowband vs. spread
    spectrum, or diverse codes.
    Using time diversity will defeat short-term interferences;
    spatial diversity combats very local causes such as multipath fading;
    narrowband and spread spectrum are relatively innocuous to one another and
    can be used for diversity in the presence of the other.
    </t>


    </section>
      <!--Reliability in the Context of RAW-->

    </section>
    <!--Reliability and Availability-->
    <!--  11111111111111111111    -->



    <section anchor="problem" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>The RAW problem</name>
   <t>
   While the generic <xref target="RFC8557">"Deterministic Networking
   Problem Statement"</xref> applies to both the wired and the wireless media,
   the methods to achieve RAW must extend those used to support time-sensitive
   networking over wires, as a RAW solution has to address less consistent
   transmissions, energy conservation and shared spectrum efficiency.
   </t>
   <t>

   Operating at the Layer-3, RAW does not change the wireless technology at the lower layers. OTOH, it can further increase diversity in the spatial,
   time, code, and frequency domains by enabling multiple link-layer wired and
   wireless technologies in parallel or sequentially, for a higher resilience
   and a wider applicability. RAW can also provide homogeneous services to
   critical applications beyond the boundaries of a single subnetwork, e.g.,
   controlling the use of diverse radio access technologies to optimize the
   end-to-end application experience.
   </t>
      <t>
   RAW improves the DetNet services by providing elements that are specialized
   for transporting IP flows over deterministic radios technologies such as
   listed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"/>.
   Conceptually, RAW is agnostic to the radio layer underneath though the
   capability to schedule transmissions is assumed.
   How the PHY is programmed to do so, and whether the radio is single-hop
   or meshed, are unknown at the IP layer and not part of the RAW abstraction.
   Nevertheless, cross-layer optimizations may take place to ensure proper
   link awareness (think, link quality) and packet handling (think, scheduling).
      </t>
      <t>
   The <xref target="RFC8655">"Deterministic Networking Architecture"</xref> is
   composed of three planes: the Application (User) Plane, the Controller Plane,
   and the Network Plane.
   The DetNet Network Plane is composed a Dataplane (packet forwarding) and an
   Operational Plane where OAM operations take place.
   In the Network Plane, the DetNet service sub-layer
   focuses on flow protection (e.g., using redundancy) and can be fully operated
   at Layer-3, while the DetNet forwarding sub-layer that associates the flows to the
   paths, ensures the availability of the necessary resources, must leverage
   Layer-2 functionalities for timely delivery to the next DetNet system.
      </t>
      <t>
   The RAW Architecture extends the DetNet Network Plane, to accommodate one or
   multiple hops of homogeneous or heterogeneous wired and wireless technologies.
   RAW adds reactivity to the DetNet service sub-layer to compensate the dynamics
   for the radio links in terms of lossiness and bandwidth. This may apply for
   instance to mesh networks as illustrated in <xref target ="FigCPF"/>, or
   diverse radio access networks as illustrated in <xref target ="Figranp2"/>.
      </t>


    <t>
    As opposed to wired links, the availability and performance of an individual
    wireless link cannot be trusted over the long term; it will vary with
    transient service discontinuity, and any lane that includes wireless
    hops is bound to face short periods of high loss. On the other hand, being
    broadcast in nature, the wireless medium provides capabilities that are
    atypical on modern wired links and that the RAW Architecture leverages
    opportunistically to improve the end-to-end reliability over a collection of
    paths.
    </t>
    <t>
    Those capabilities include:
    </t>
    <dl>
    <dt>Promiscuous Overhearing:</dt><dd> Because the medium is broadcast as
    opposed to physically point to point like a wire, more than one
    node in the forward direction of the packet may hear or overhear a
    transmission, and the reception by one may compensate the loss by another.
    The concept of path can be revisited in favor multipoint to multipoint
    progress in the orward direction and statistical chances of successful
    reception of any of the transmissions by any of the receivers.
    </dd>
    <dt>L2-aware routing:</dt><dd> As the quality and speed of a link variates
    over time, the concept of metric must also be revisited. Shortest path loses
    its absolute value, and hop count turns into a bad idea as the link budget
    drops with the distance. Routing over radio requires both 1) a new and more
    dynamic sense of the link, with new protocols such as DLEP and L2-trigger to
    maintain L3 up to date with the link quality and availability, and 2) a new
    approach to multipath routing, where non-equal cost multipath becomes the
    norm as shortest path loses its meaning with the instability of the metrics.
    </dd>
    <dt>ARQ, FEC and codes:</dt><dd>Though feasible on any technology, proactive
    (forward) and reactive (ARQ) error correction are typical to the wireless
    media. Bounded latency can still be obtained on a wireless link while
    operating those technologies, provided that the extra transmission happens
    within the budget allocated to that hop, or that the introduced delay is
    compensated along the path. In the case of coded fragments and retries, it
    makes sense to variate all the possible physical properties of the
    transmission to reduce the chances that the same effect causes the loss of
    both original and redundant transimissions.
    </dd>
    <dt>Relay Coordination and constructive interference:</dt><dd>Though it can be difficult to achieve at high speed, a fine time synchronization and a
    precise sense of phase allows the energy from multiple coordinated senders
    to add up at the receiver and actually improve the signal quality,
    compensating for either distance or physical objects in the Fresnel zone
    that would reduce the link budget.
    </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
    RAW and DetNet route application flows that require a special
    treatment along the paths that will provide that treatment.
    This may be seen as a form of Path Aware Networking and may be subject to
    impediments documented in <xref target="RFC9049"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
   The establishment of a path is not in-scope for RAW. It may be, e.g., the
   product of a centralized Controller Plane Function (CPF)
   like a Path computation Element (PCE) <xref target="RFC4655"/>, or may be
   computed in a distributed fashion ala
   Resource ReSerVation Protocol (RSVP) <xref target="RFC2205"/>.
   On the other hand, RAW leverages DetNet Network Plane enhancements to
   optimize the use of the paths and match the quality of the transmissions over
   time.
   </t>
   <t>
   As opposed to wired
   networks, the action of installing a path over a set of wireless links
   may be very slow relative to the speed at which the radio conditions vary,
   and it makes sense in the wireless case to provide redundant forwarding
   solutions along a  (see <xref target="pt"/>) and to leave it
   to the Network Plane to select which of those forwarding solutions are to be
   used for a given packet based on the current conditions.
      </t>
      <t>
   RAW distinguishes the longer time scale at which routes are computed from the
   the shorter time scale where forwarding decisions are made for a limited time
   RAW Network Plane operations happen at a time scale that sits between the
   routing and the forwarding time scales, on one DetNet flow, to select a DetNet
   path within the resources delineated by a recovery graph (see <xref target="trk"/>).
   The recovery graph is
   preestablished and installed by means outside of the scope of RAW; it may be
   strict or loose depending on whether each or just a subset of the hops are
   observed and controlled by RAW.
      </t>
      <t>
   The RAW Architecture is based on an abstract OODA Loop (Observe, Orient, Decide,
   Act). The generic concept involves:
      </t>
      <ol>
      <li> Operational Plane measurement protocols for Operations, Administration
      and Maintenance (OAM) to Observe some or all hops along a recovery graph as well as
      the end-to-end packet delivery
      </li>
      <li>
      The DetNet Controller Plane Function (CPF) is split with an
      optional asynchronous CPF (aCPF) that reports
      data and information such as link statistics to be used asynchronously
      by the routing CPF (rCPF) to compute, install, and maintain the
      recovery graphs, e.g., by generating knowledge and wisdom such as a trained model
      for link quality prediction, which in turn can be used by the aCPF to
      Orient the Path selection by the PLR within the RAW OODA loop.
      </li>
      <li> An Operational Plane PLR that hosts the Decision function of which DetNet Paths to use for the future packets that will be routed within the recovery graph
      </li>
      <li> Packet (hybrid) ARQ, Replication, Elimination and Ordering Dataplane
      actions that operate at the DetNet Service sub-layer to increase the
      reliability of the end-to-end transmissions. The RAW architecture also
      covers in-situ signaling when the decision is Acted by a node that
      down the recovery graph from the PLR.
      </li>
      </ol>
   <t> The overall OODA Loop optimizes the use of redundancy to achieve the
   required reliability and availability Service Level Agreement (SLA) while
   minimizing the use of constrained resources such as spectrum and battery.
   </t>


    </section>      <!-- The RAW problem -->
     </section>   <!-- Reliable and Available Wireless -->

    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

<section anchor="model" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The RAW Conceptual Model</name>
    <t>
    RAW inherits the conceptual model described in section 4 of the DetNet
    Architecture <xref target="RFC8655"/> as illustrated in 
	<xref target='FigLayers'/>, which also shows example reliability Functions
	in the different layers. RAW extends DetNet with Point of Local Repair 
	(PLR, see <xref target='PLRpce'/>) to provide additional agility against 
	transmission loss. The PLR can act, e.g., based on indications from the
    wireless layer or based on OAM.	
    </t>

<figure anchor="FigLayers">
          <name>Wireless layer and DetNet sub-layers</name>
       <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt="">
                   .
                   .
     +-----------------------------+
     |                             |
     |  DetNet Service sub-layer   | (e.g., (PREOF)
     |                             | 	 
     +-----------------------------+
     |                             |
     | DetNet Forwarding sub-layer |
     |                             |
     |           _____    _____    |
     |          | PLR +--+ OAM |   |
     |           -+---    -----    |
     |            | ^              |
     |            | |              |
     |         ___v_+___           | 	 
     +--------+ RAW API +----------+
     |         ---------           |
     |    Wireless/Radio Layer     | (e.g., (H)ARQ)
     |                             | 	 
     +-----------------------------+
                   .
</artwork>
</figure>
    <t>
	The RAW API enables interactions between the reliability functions provided
	by the wireless technology and the reliability functions provided by DetNet.
	Thus, the RAW aPI enables cross-layer optimizations to improve reliability. 
	</t>

<section anchor="plane" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The RAW Planes</name>
    <t>
   A RAW Network Plane may be strict (as illustrated in <xref target='FigDN2'/>
   or loose (as illustrated in <xref target='FigDN3'/>, depending
   on whether RAW observes and takes actions on all hops or not. For instance,
   the packets between two wireless entities may be relayed over a wired
   infrastructure such as a Wi-Fi extended service set (ESS) or a 5G Core; in
   that case, RAW observes and controls the transmission over the wireless first
   and last hops, as well as end-to-end metrics such as latency, jitter, and
   delivery ratio. This operation is loose since the structure and properties of
   the wired infrastructure are ignored, and may be either controlled by other
   means such as DetNet/TSN, or neglected in the face of the wireless hops.

    </t><t>
   The RAW Nodes are DetNet relays that operate in the RAW Network Plane and
   are capable of additional diversity mechanisms and measurement functions
   related to the radio interface.
   RAW leverages a CPF that operates inside the RAW Nodes (typically the Ingress
   Edge Nodes) to dynamically adapt the path of the packets and optimizes the
   resource usage.
    </t><t>
   An RAW-enhanced rCPF interacts
   with RAW Nodes over a Southbound API. It consumes data and information from
   the network and generates knowledge and wisdom to help steer the traffic optimally
   inside a recovery graph.
    </t>
<figure anchor="FigCPF">
          <name>RAW Nodes</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">

                         DetNet Routing

        rCPF               rCPF          rCPF                 rCPF


                       Southbound API
   _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
 _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-


                 RAW  --/   RAW  --/   RAW  --/   RAW
             /-- Node  /--  Node  /--  Node  /--  Node --/
  Ingress --/    /          /                           /-- Egress
  End           /          /         .. .                   End
  Node   ---/   /          /       .. ..  .             /-- Node
           /-- RAW  --/   RAW     ( non-RAW ) -- RAW --/
               Node  /--  Node --- ( Nodes  )   Node
                                      ... .
  --/   wireless           wired
   /--  link           --- link
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
   When a new flow is defined, the rCPF uses it current knowledge of
   the network to build a new recovery graph between an Ingress End System and an Egress
   End System for that flow; it indicates to the RAW Nodes where the PREOF and/or radio 
   diversity and reliability operations may be actioned in the Network Plane.
  </t>
  <ul>
  <li>
    The recovery graph may be strict, meaning that the
    DetNet forwarding sub-layer operations are enforced end-to-end
  </li><li>
    The recovery graph may be expressed loosely to enable traversing a non-RAW subnetwork
    as in <xref target='FigDN3'/>.
    In that case, RAW can not leverage end-to-end DetNet and cannot provide
    latency guarantees.
    The non-RAW subnetwork is neglected in the RAW computation, that is,
    considered jitterless, and infinitely reliable and/or available in comparison
    with the links between RAW nodes, so loss and jitter that is measured
    end-to-end is attributed to the RAW hops (typically an access link).
    </li>
    </ul>
    <t>
    A local asynchronous CPF in the RAW node reports the Link-Layer metrics
    to the rCPF in a time-aggregated, e.g., statistical fashion.
    Example Link-Layer metrics include typical Link
    bandwidth (the medium speed depends dynamically on the PHY mode), number of
    flows (bandwidth that can be reserved for a flow depends on the number and
    size of flows sharing the spectrum) and average and mean squared deviation
    of availability and reliability figures such as Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR)
    over long periods of time.
    </t><t>
    Based on those metrics, the DetNet r CPF installs the recovery graph with enough
    redundant forwarding solutions to ensure that the Network Plane can reliably
    deliver the packets within a System Level Agreement (SLA) associated to the
    flows that it transports.
    The SLA defines end-to-end reliability and availability requirements, where
    reliability may be expressed as a successful delivery in order and within a
    bounded delay of at least one copy of a packet.
    </t><t>
    Depending on the use case and the SLA, the recovery graph may comprise non-RAW
    segments, either interleaved inside the recovery graph, or all the way to
    the Egress End Node (e.g., a server in the Internet). RAW observes the
    Lower-Layer Links between RAW nodes (typically, radio links) and the
    end-to-end Network Layer operation to decide at all times which of the 
    diversity schemes is actioned by which RAW Nodes.
    </t><t>
    Once a recovery graph is established, per-segment and end-to-end reliability and
    availability statistics are periodically reported to the rCPF
    to assure that the SLA can be met or have it recompute the recovery graph if not.
    </t>

    </section> <!--The RAW Network Plane -->

<section anchor="layers" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>RAW vs. Upper and Lower Layers</name>

    <t>RAW improves the reliability of transmissions and the availability of the
    communication resources, but does not provide scheduling and shaping, so RAW
    itself does not provide guarantees such as latency for the application
    payload. Rather, it should be seen as a dynamic optimization of the use of
    redundancy to maintain it within certain boundaries. For instance, ARQ is
    operated by the lower layers and RAW will only abstract the concept and hint
    the lower layers on the desired outcome, as opposed to performing the
    retries at Layer-3.
    </t>
    <t>
    Guarantees such as bounded latency depend on the upper layers (Transport or
    Application) to provide the payload in volumes and at times that match the
    contract with the DetNet sub-layers and the layers below. Excess of
    incoming traffic at the DetNet Ingress will cause either dropping, queueing,
    or reclassification of the packets, and entail loss, latency, or jitter, and
    moot the guarantees that are provided inside the DetNet Network.
    </t>
    <t>
    When the traffic from upper layers matches the expectation of the lower
    layers, RAW still depends on the lower layers to provide the timing and
    physical resources guarantees that are needed to match the traffic SLA.
    When the availability of the physical resource varies, RAW will act on the
    distribution of the traffic to leverage alternates within a finite set of
    potential resources.
    </t>


    </section> <!--The RAW Network Plane -->

<section anchor="DetNet" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>RAW and DetNet</name>
<t>
  RAW leverages the DetNet Forwarding sub-layer and requires the support of
  in-situ OAM in DetNet Transit Nodes (see fig 3 of <xref target="RFC8655"/>
  for the dynamic acquisition of link capacity and state to maintain a strict RAW
  service, end-to-end, over a DetNet Network. RAW enhances DetNet to improve the
  protection against link errors such as transient flapping that are far more
  common in wireless links. Nevertheless, the RAW methods are for the most part
  applicable to wired links as well, e.g., when energy savings are desirable and
  the available path diversity exceeds 1+1 linear redundancy.
</t>
<t>
  RAW adds sub-layer functions that operate in the DetNet Operational Plane.
  The RAW Operational sub-layer typically runs only in the DetNet Ingress Edge Node
  or End System, though it may also run in DetNet Relay Nodes when the RAW
  Control sub-layer is distributed along the recovery graph.
  The RAW Operational sub-layer functionality includes the PLR that decides the
  DetNet Path for the future packets of a flows along the DetNet Path through
  specific signaling, and the OAM Supervisor that triggers, and learns from, 
  OAM observations, and feeds the PLR for its next decision.
</t>
<t>
  RAW extends the DetNet Stack (see fig 4 of <xref target="RFC8655"/>) with
  additional functionality at the DetNet Service sub-layer for the actuation of
  the PLR decision.
  Layer-3 in general and DetNet in particular operates on abstractions of the
  lower layers and through APIs to control those abstractions. For instance,
  DetNet already leverages lower layers for time-sensitive operations such as
  time synchronization and traffic shapers. Because the performances of the
  radio layers are subject to rapid changes, so RAW needs more dynamic gauges
  and knobs. To that effect, the RAW API enables interactions between the 
  reliability functions provided by the wireless technology and the reliability 
  functions provided by DetNet. That is, the RAW API provides a radio 
  abstraction to the DetNet layer. The RAW API can be used  to push reliability
  and timing hints like suggest X retries (min, max) within a time window, or 
  send unicast (one next hop) or multicast (for overhearing). The other way 
  around RAW needs hints about the radio conditions like L2 triggers (RSSI, 
  LQI, ETX) over all the wireless hops. This information is useful to both the
  aCPF and the PLR.
  </t>
  <t>
  The RAW Service sub-layer also adds the OAM Propagator that (re)generates the
  OAM information as it is formed and propagated In-Band or Out-of-Band.
  The RAW Service sub-layer may be present in DetNet Edge and Relay Nodes, though
  the PREOF Actuator has no operation in the Egress Edge Node.
</t>


<figure anchor="FigDN">
          <name>RAW functional posture within DetNet sub-layers</name>
       <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt="">

 +------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+
 |                              | |                                |
.....................................................................
 |                              | |                                |
 | +--------------------------+ | | +----------------------------+ |
 | |     aCPF                 | | | |         aCPF               | |
 | +--------------------------+ | | +----------------------------+ |
 | +----------+  +------------+ | | .-.-.-.-.-.--.  .-.-.-.-.-.--. |
 | | PLR      |  | OAM        | | | | Distr. PLR |  | Distr. OAM | |
 | |          |  | Supervisor | | | |            |  | Supervisor | |
 | +----------+  +------------+ | | .-.-.-.-.-.--.  .-.-.-.-.-.--. |
 |                              | |    optional         optional   |
    RAW Operational sub-layer
.....................................................................
    DetNet Service sub-layer
 |                              | |                                |
 | +----------+  +------------+ | | +------------+  +------------+ |
 | | PREOF    |  |  OAM       | | | |  PREOF     |  |  OAM       | |
 | | Actuator |  |  Observer  | | | |  Actuator  |  |  Observer  | |
 | +----------+  +------------+ | | +------------+  +------------+ |
 |                              | |                                |
    DetNet Service sub-layer
.....................................................................
    DetNet Forwarding sub-layer
 |                              | |                                |
 |               +------------+ | |                 +------------+ |
 |               |In-Situ OAM | | |                 |In-Situ OAM | |
 |               +------------+ | |                 +------------+ |
 |                              | |                                |
 +------------------------------+ +--------------------------------+

         End System or                       Relay
       Ingress Edge Node                     Node

</artwork>
</figure>

<t> There are 2 main proposed models to deploy RAW and DetNet. In the first
  model (strict) illustrated in <xref target="FigDN2"/>, RAW operates over a
  continuous DetNet Service end-to-end between the Ingress and the Egress Edge
  Nodes or End Systems.
</t>
<t>
  A minimal Forwarding sub-layer service is provided at all DetNet Nodes
  to ensure that the OAM information flows. Relay Nodes may or may not support
  RAW services, and the Edge nodes do support RAW. DetNet guarantees such as
  latency are provided end-to-end, and RAW supports the DetNet Service to
  optimize the use of resources.
</t>


<figure anchor="FigDN2">
          <name>(Strict) RAW over DetNet</name>
       <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt="">

--------------------Flow Direction---------------------------------->

+---------+
| RAW     |
| Control |
+---------+                           +---------+        +---------+
| RAW +   |                           | RAW +   |        | RAW +   |
| DetNet  |                           | DetNet  |        | DetNet  |
| Service |                           | Service |        | Service |
+---------+---------------------------+---------+--------+---------+
|                       DetNet                                     |
|                     Forwarding                                   |
+------------------------------------------------------------------+

  Ingress             Transit            Relay              Egress
  Edge      ...       Nodes     ...      Nodes     ...        Edge
  Node                                                        Node

&lt;--------------------Full Guarantees------------------------------->

</artwork>
</figure>


<t> In the second model (loose), illustrated in <xref target="FigDN3"/>, RAW
  operates over a partial DetNet Service where typically only the Ingress and
  the Egress End Systems support RAW. The DetNet Domain may extend beyond the
  Ingress node, or there may be a DetNet domain starting at an Ingress
  Edge Node at the first hop after the End System.
</t>
<t>
  In the loose model, RAW cannot observe the hops in network, and the path
  beyond the first hop is opaque; RAW can still observe the end-to-end
  behavior and use Layer-3 measurements to decide whether to replicate a packet
  and select the first hop interface(s).
</t>
<figure anchor="FigDN3">
          <name>Loose RAW</name>
       <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt="">

--------------------Flow Direction---------------------------------->

+---------+
| RAW     |
| Control |
+---------+            +---------+                       +---------+
| RAW +   |            | DetNet  |                       | RAW +   |
| DetNet  |            |  Only   |                       | DetNet  |
| Service |            | Service |                       | Service |
+---------+----------------------+---+               +---+---------+
|          DetNet                    |               |   DetNet    |
|         Forwarding                 |               | Forwarding  |
+------------------------------------+               +-------------+

 Ingress    Transit       Relay           Internet           Egress
 End  ...   Nodes   ...   Nodes    ...                ...       End
 System                                                      System

&lt;----------------------No Guarantee-------------------------------->

</artwork>
</figure>


    </section>      <!-- RAW and DetNet -->



    <!--  1111111111111   -->


</section> <!-- The RAW Conceptual Model -->
<section anchor="control" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The RAW Control Loop</name>


    <section anchor="timescale" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Routing Time Scale vs. Forwarding Time Scale</name>
      <t>
   With DetNet, the Controller Plane Function handles the routing
   computation and maintenance. With RAW, the routing part of the CPF (rCPF) is
   segregated from the RAW Control Loop, so it may reside outside of the RAW
   network. To achieve RAW capabilities, the rCPF is enhanced to generate the
   information required by the local aCPF, which acts as the orientation component in
   the loop. The rCPF may, e.g., propose DetNet Paths to be used as a reflex
   action in response to network events, or by provide aggregated history that
   the aCPF can use to make an oriented decision.
   </t>
<t>
   In a wireless mesh, the path to the DetNet CPF can be expensive and
   slow, possibly going across the whole mesh and back.
   Reaching to the CPF can also be slow in regards to the speed
   of events that affect the forwarding operation at the radio layer.
   Note that a distributed routing protocol may also take time and
   consume excessive wireless resources to reconverge to a new optimized state.

      </t><t>
   As a result, the DetNet CPF is not expected to be aware of and to react to
   very transient changes. The abstraction of a link at the routing level is
   expected to use statistical metrics that aggregate the behavior of a link
   over long periods of time, and  represent its properties as shades of gray as
   opposed to numerical values such as a link quality indicator, or a boolean
   value for either up or down.
      </t><t>

   The interaction with the (remote) RAW rCPF is handled by a (local)
   aCPF that builds reports to the rCPF and digests
   the control information back, to be used inside a forwarding control loop
   for traffic steering.
      </t>

         <figure anchor="Figcontrol">
          <name>Time Scales</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
       <![CDATA[
               +----------------+
               |     DetNet     |
               |    Routing     |
               |      CPF       |
               +----------------+
                       ^
                       |
                      Slow
                       |
   _-._-._-._-._-._-.  |  ._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
 _-._-._-._-._-._-._-. | _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
                       |
                    Expensive
                       |
                ....   |  .......
            ....    .  | .       .......
         ....          v               ...
       ..    A-------B-------C---D        ..
    ...     /  \           /      \      ..
   .       I ----M-------N--***-- E        ..
   ..       \         /         /         ...
     ..      P--***--Q-----M---R        ....
       ..                              ....
        .   <----- Fast ------->    ....
         .......                ....
                .................

*** = flapping at this time
    ]]>
       </artwork>
       </figure>
      <t>
   In the case of wireless, the changes that affect the forwarding decision can
   happen frequently and often for short durations, e.g., a mobile object moves
   between a transmitter and a receiver, and will cancel the line of sight
   transmission for a few seconds, or a radar measures the depth of a pool and
   interferes on a particular channel for a split second.
      </t>
      <t>
   There is thus a desire to separate the long term computation of the route and
   the short term forwarding decision. In that model, the routing operation
   computes a recovery graph that enables multiple Non-Equal Cost Multi-Path
   (N-ECMP) forwarding solutions along so-called protection paths, and leaves
   it to the Network Plane to make
   the per-packet decision of which of these possibilities should be used.
      </t>
      <t>
   In the wired world, and more specifically in the context of Traffic
   Engineering (TE), an alternate path can be used upon the detection of a
   failure in the main path, e.g., using OAM in MPLS-TP or BFD over a
   collection of SD-WAN tunnels. RAW
   formalizes a forwarding time scale that is an order(s) of magnitude shorter
   than the controller plane routing time scale, and separates the protocols
   and metrics that are used at both scales.
   Routing can operate on long term statistics such as delivery
   ratio over minutes to hours, but as a first approximation can ignore flapping.
   On the other hand, the RAW forwarding decision is made at the scale of the packet rate, and uses information that must be pertinent at the present time for the current transmission(s).
      </t>

    </section >
    <!--Routing Time Scale vs. Forwarding Time Scale-->

<section anchor="ooda" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>A OODA Loop</name>
      <t>
   OODA (Observe, Orient, Decide, Act) is a generic formalism to represent the
   operational steps in a Control Loop.
   The RAW Architecture applies that generic model to continuously optimize the
   spectrum and energy used to forward packets within a recovery graph, instantiating the
   OODA steps as follows:
      </t>
      <dl>
      <dt>Observe:</dt><dd> Network Plane measurements, including protocols for
      Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM), to Observe the local
      state of the links and some or all hops along a recovery graph as well as
      the end-to-end packet delivery, more in <xref target = "aom" />;
      </dd>
      <dt>Orient:</dt><dd>
      An asynchronous CPF that reports data and information such as the link
      statistics, and leverages offline-computed wisdom and knowledge to Orient
      the PLR for its forwarding decision, more in <xref target = "pce" />;
      </dd>
      <dt>Decide:</dt><dd> A local PLR that decides which DetNet Path to use
      for the future packet(s) that are routed along the recovery graph,
      more in <xref target = "PLRpce" />;
      </dd>
      <dt>Act:</dt><dd> PREOF Dataplane
      actions are controlled from the DetNet Service sub-layer to increase the
      reliability of the end-to-end transmission. The RAW architecture also
      covers in-situ signaling when the decision is Acted by a node that
      down the recovery graph from the PLR, more in 
	  <xref target = "reliability" />.
      </dd>
      </dl>
      <figure anchor="oodaloop">
          <name>The RAW OODA Loop</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
<![CDATA[

     +-------> Orient (aCPF) -------+
     |        reflex actions        |
     |       pre-trained model      |
     |             ...              |
     |                              v
 Observe (OAM)                Decide (PLR)
     ^                              |
     |                              |
     |                              |
     +-------- Act (PREOF) <--------+
                At DetNet
             Service sub-layer

]]></artwork>
</figure>
   <t> The overall OODA Loop optimizes the use of redundancy to achieve the
   required reliability and availability Service Level Agreement (SLA) while
   minimizing the use of constrained resources such as spectrum and battery.
   </t>


</section > <!-- A OODA Loop -->
<section anchor="aom" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>Observe: The RAW OAM </name><t>
    RAW In-situ OAM operation in the Network Plane may observe either a full
    recovery graph or the DetNet Path that is being used at this time. As packets may be load
    balanced, replicated, eliminated, and / or fragmented for Network Coding
    (NC) forward error correction (FEC), the RAW In-situ operation needs to be
    able to signal which operation occured to an individual packet.
    </t>
    <t>
    Active RAW OAM may
    be needed to observe the unused segments and evaluate the desirability of
    a rerouting decision.
    </t>
    <t>
    Finally, the RAW Service sub-layer Assurance may observe the individual PREOF
    operation of a relay node to ensure that it is conforming; this might
    require injecting an OAM packet at an upstream point inside the recovery graph and
    extracting that packet at another point downstream before it reaches the
    egress.
    </t><t>
    This observation feeds the RAW
    PLR that makes the decision on which path is used at which RAW
    Node, for one a small continuous series of packets.
     </t>
<figure anchor="Figranp2">
          <name>Observed Links in Radio Access Protection</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
<![CDATA[
                                   ...   ..
                RAN 1  -----  ...      ..  ...
             /              .    ..          ....
+-------+  /              .            ..      ....    +------+
|Ingress|-                .                     .....  |Egress|
|  End  |------ RAN 2 -- .       Internet       ....---| End  |
|System |-                ..                   .....   |System|
+-------+  \               .               ......      +------+
             \               ...   ...     .....
                RAN n  --------  ...   .....

       <------------------> <-------------------->
          Observed by OAM       Opaque to OAM

]]></artwork>
</figure>
   <t>
    In the case of a End-to-End Protection in a Wireless Mesh, the recovery graph is strict and congruent
    with the path so all links are observed.
    </t>
    <t>
    Conversely, in the case of Radio Access Protection illustrated in <xref target="Figranp2"/>, the recovery graph is Loose and only the first hop is observed; the rest of the path is abstracted and considered infinitely reliable.
    The loss if a packet is attributed to the first hop Radio Access Network (RAN),
    even if a particular loss effectively happens farther down the path.
    In that case, RAW enables technology diversity (e.g. Wi-Fi and 5G) which in
    turn improves the diversity in spectrum usage.
    </t>
    <t>
    The Links that are not observed by OAM are opaque to it, meaning that the
    OAM information is carried across and possibly echoed as data, but there is
    no information capture in intermediate nodes. In the example above, the
    Internet is opaque and not controlled by RAW; still the RAW OAM measures the
    end-to-end latency and delivery ratio for packets sent via each if RAN 1,
    RAN 2 and RAN 3, and determines whether a packet should be sent over either
    or a collection of those access links.
    </t>




</section>
    <!-- Observe: The RAW OAM -->


<section anchor="pce" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>Orient: The RAW-enhanced DetNet Operational Plane</name>

   <t>
   RAW separates the long time scale at which a recovery graph is elaborated and installed,
   from the short time scale at which the forwarding decision is taken for one
   or a few packets (see in <xref target="timescale"/>) that will experience the
   same path until the network conditions evolve and another path is selected
   within the same recovery graph.
   </t>
   <t>
   The recovery graph computation is out of scope, but RAW expects that the CPF
   that installs the recovery graph also provides related knowledge
   in the form of meta data about the links, segments and possible DetNet Paths.
   That meta data can be a pre-digested statistical model, and may include
   prediction of future flaps and packet loss, as well as recommended actions
   when that happens.
   </t>
   <t>
   The meta data may include:
   </t>
   <ul>
   <li>
   A set of Pre-Determined DetNet Paths that are prepared to match expected link
   degradation profiles, so the DDCPEs can take reflex rerouting actions when
   facing a degradation that matches one such profile.
   </li>
   <li>
   Link Quality Statistics history and pre-trained models, e.g., to predict the
   short-term variation of quality of the links in a recovery graph
   </li>
   </ul>
   <t>
   The recovery graph is installed with measurable objectives that are computed
   by the rCPF to achieve the RAW SLA. The objectives can be expressed as any of
   maximum number of packet lost in a row, bounded latency, maximal jitter,
   maximum number of interleaved out of order packets,
   average number of copies received at the elimination point, and maximal
   delay between the first and the last received copy of the same packet.
   </t>
</section>
    <!-- Orient: The Path Computation Engine -->

<section anchor="PLRpce" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>Decide: The Point of Local Repair</name>
 <t>
    The RAW OODA Loop operates at the path selection time scale to provide
    agility vs. the brute force approach of flooding the whole recovery graph.
    The OODA Loop controls, within the redundant solutions that are proposed
    by the acynchronous CPF, which will be used for each packet to provide a
    Reliable and Available service while minimizing the waste of constrained
    resources.
    </t><t>
    To that effect, RAW defines the Point of Local Repair (PLR) as a synchronous
    CPF that performs rapid local adjustments of the forwarding tables within
    the diversity that the asynchronous CPF has in store for the recovery graph.
    The PLR enables to exploit the richer forwarding capabilities at a faster 
	time scale over the smaller domain that is the recovery graph, in either a
	loose or a strict fashion.
    </t>
   <t>
    The PLR operates on metrics that evolve faster, but that need to be
    advertised at a fast rate but only locally, within the recovery graph, and reacts on
    the metrics updates by changing the DetNet path in use for the affected
    flows.
   </t>
   <t>
    The rapid changes in the forwarding decisions are made and contained within
    the scope of a recovery graph and the actions of the PLR are not signaled outside
    the recovery graph. This is as opposed to the rCPF that must observe
    the whole network and optimize all the recovery graphs globally, which can only be
    done at a slow pace and using long-term statistical metrics, as presented in
    <xref target="PCEPLRtable"/>.
    </t>


    <table anchor="PCEPLRtable"><name>CPF vs. PLR</name>
   <thead>
      <tr>
       <th> </th>
		   <th align='center'> rCPF </th>
		   <th align='center'> PLR (In Scope) </th>
      </tr>

   </thead><tbody>

			<tr><td>Operation</td>
    			<td align='center'>Typically Centralized</td>
    			<td align='center'>Source-Routed or Distributed</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Communication
</td>
    			<td align='center'>Slow, expensive</td>
    			<td align='center'>Fast, local</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Time Scale</td>
    			<td align='center'>hours and above</td>
    			<td align='center'>seconds and below</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Network Size</td>
    			<td align='center'>Large, many recovery graphs to optimize globally</td>
    			<td align='center'>Small, within one recovery graph</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Considered Metrics</td>
    			<td align='center'>Averaged, Statistical, Shade of grey</td>
    			<td align='center'>Instant values / boolean condition</td>
        </tr>



    </tbody>
    </table>
    <t>
    The PLR sits in the DetNet Service sub-Layer of Edge and Relay Nodes. On the
    one hand, it operates on the packet flow, learning the recovery graph and path
    selection information from the packet, possibly making local decision and
    retagging the packet to indicate so. On the other hand, the PLR interacts
    with the lower layers (through triggers and DLEP) and with its peers
    (through iOAM and oOAM) to obtain up-to-date information about its links and
    the quality of the overall recovery graph, respectively, as illustrated in
    <xref target="Figlearn"/>.
    </t>

<figure anchor="Figlearn">
          <name>PLR Interfaces</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
            |
     packet | going
   down the | stack
 +==========v==========+=====================+=====================+
 |   (iOAM + iCTRL)    | (L2 Triggers, DLEP) |       (oOAM)        |
 +==========v==========+=====================+=====================+
 |     Learn from      |                     |    Learn from       |
 |    packet tagging   >       Maintain      <    end-to-end       |
 +----------v----------+      Forwarding     |    OAM packets      |
 | Forwarding decision <        State        +---------^-----------|
 +----------v----------+                     |      Enrich or      |
 +    Retag Packet     |  Learn abstracted   >     Regenerate      |
 |    and Forward      | metrics about Links |     OAM packets     |
 +..........v..........+..........^..........+.........^.v.........+
 |                          Lower layers                           |
 +..........v.....................^....................^.v.........+
      frame | sent          Frame | L2 Ack        oOAM | | packet
       over | wireless        In  |                 In | | and out
            v                     |                    | v
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</section>
    <!--PCE vs. PLR-->


    <!--  11111111111111111    -->
    <section anchor="reliability" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Act: DetNet Path Selection and reliability functions</name>
      <t>
    The main action by the PLR is the swapping of the DetNet Path within the
    recovery graph for the future packets.
    The candidate DetNet Paths represent different energy and spectrum profiles,
    and provide protection against different failures.
    </t>
    <t>The RAW API enriches the DetNet protection services (PREOF)
    with potential possiblity to control lower layer one-hop reliability functions that are more
    typical to wireless than wires, including Automatic Repeat reQuest (ARQ),
    Forward Error Correction (FEC), Hybrid ARQ (HARQ) that includes both, and
    other techniques such as overhearing and constructive interferences.
    Because RAW may be leveraged on wired links, e.g., to save power, it is not
    expected that all lower layers support all those capabilities.
    </t>
    <t>
    RAW manipulates abstractions of the lower layer services to hint on the
    desired outcome, and the lower layer acts on those hints to provide
    the best approximation of that outcome, e.g., a level of reliability
    for one-hop transmission within a bounded budget of time and/or energy.
    Thus, the RAW API makes possible cross-layer optimization for 
	reliability depending on the actual abstraction provided. That is, some 
    reliability functions are controlled from Layer-3 using an abstract 
	interface, while they are really operated at the lower layers.
    </t>
    <t>
    The RAW Path Selection can be implemented in both centralized and distributed
    scheduling approaches.
    In the centralized approach, the PLR may obtain a set of pre-computed DetNet
    paths matching a set of expected failures, and apply the appropriate DetNet
    paths for the current state of the wireless links.
    In the distributed approach, the signaling in the packet may be more
    abstract than an explicit Path, and the PLR decision might be revised along
    the select DetNet Path based on a better knowledge of the rest of the way.
    </t>
    <t>
    The dynamic DetNet Path selection in RAW avoids the waste of critical
    resources such as spectrum and energy while providing for the
    guaranteed SLA, e.g., by rerouting and/or adding redundancy only when a
    spike of loss is observed.
    </t>




</section>      <!-- Act: The reliability Functions-->

</section>
   <!-- The RAW Control Loop -->

    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->



    <section anchor="SecurityConsiderations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
    <t>
    RAW uses all forms of diversity including radio technology and physical path
    to increase the reliability and availability in the face of unpredictable
    conditions. While this is not done specifically to defeat an attacker, the
    amount of diversity used in RAW makes an attack harder to achieve.
    </t>




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Layer-2 encryption</name>
    <t>
    Radio networks typically encrypt at the MAC layer to protect the
    transmission. If the encryption is per pair of peers, then certain
    RAW operations like promiscuous overhearing become impossible.
    </t>

      </section><!-- Layer-2 encryption -->
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Forced Access</name>
    <t>
    A RAW policy may typically select the cheapest collection of links that
    matches the requested SLA, e.g., use free Wi-Fi vs. paid 3GPP access. By
    defeating the cheap connectivity (e.g., PHY-layer interference) the attacker
    can force an End System to use the paid access and increase the cost of the
    transmission for the user.
    </t>

      </section><!-- Forced Access -->

    <!--  111111111111111111111    -->
    </section>
      <!--Security Considerations-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>
      <!--IANA Considerations-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>The editor wishes to thank the document co-authors:
      </t>
      <dl>
    <dt>Lou Berger:</dt><dd>Lab N</dd>
    <dt>Xavi Vilajosana:</dt><dd>Wireless Networks Research Lab, Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</dd>
    <dt>Geogios Papadopolous:</dt><dd>IMT Atlantique</dd>
    <dt>Remous-Aris Koutsiamanis:</dt><dd>IMT Atlantique</dd>
    <dt>Rex Buddenberg:</dt><dd>Individual contributor</dd>
    <dt>Greg Mirsky:</dt><dd>Ericsson</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>for their contributions to the text and ideas exposed in this document.
      </t>
    </section>
      <!--ConTributors-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

   <section><name>Acknowledgments</name>
   <t>This architecture could never have been completed without the support and
   recommendations from the DetNet Chairs Janos Farkas and Lou Berger, and
   Dave Black, the DetNet Tech Advisor.
   Many thanks to all of you.
   </t>
   <t>The authors wish to thank Balazs Varga, Dave Cavalcanti, Don Fedyk,
   Nicolas Montavont, and Fabrice Theoleyre for their in-depth reviews during
   the development of this document.
   </t>
   </section>
   <!-- Acknowledgments -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->


  </middle>
  <back>


<displayreference   target="I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless"     to="IPoWIRELESS"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"   to="RAW-TECHNOS"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases"   to="RAW-USE-CASES"/>

<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework"     to="DetNet-OAM"/>


<displayreference   target="RFC1122"                  to="INT-ARCHI"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC3272"                  to="TE"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8175"                  to="DLEP"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC3411"                  to="STD 62"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC7490"                  to="RLFA-FRR"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC5714"                  to="FRR"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8200"                  to="IPv6"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8938"                  to="DetNet-DP"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC9030"                  to="6TiSCH-ARCHI"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
    <name>Normative References</name>


<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9030.xml"/>
<!-- 6TiSCH Architecture -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml"/>
<!-- Internet Architecture -->
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4427.xml"/>
<!-- Internet Architecture -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-technologies.xml"/>
<!-- Reliable and Available Wireless Technologies -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases.xml"/>
<!-- RAW use cases -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
<!-- PCE -->


<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6291.xml"/>
<!-- Guidelines for the Use of the "OAM" Acronym in the IETF  -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7799.xml"/>
<!-- Active and Passive Metrics and Methods for OAM  -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8578.xml"/>
<!-- Deterministic Networking Use Cases -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml"/>
<!-- IPv6 -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8557.xml"/>
<!-- DetNet problem statement -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml"/>
<!-- Deterministic Networking Architecture -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8939.xml"/>
<!-- Deterministic Networking IP dataplane -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9049.xml"/>
<!-- Path Aware Networking: Obstacles to Deployment  -->

      </references>
    <!--Normative References-->


      <references>
    <name>Informative References</name>


<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml"/>
<!-- IP -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml"/>
<!-- RSVP -->


<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3272.xml"/>
<!-- TE -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3366.xml"/>
<!-- Advice to link designers on link Automatic Repeat reQuest (ARQ) -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml"/>
<!-- An Architecture for Describing Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4090.xml"/>
<!-- Fast Reroute Extensions to RSVP-TE -->



<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5880.xml"/>
<!-- BFD -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5714.xml"/>
<!--  IP Fast Reroute Framework -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7490.xml"/>
<!--   Remote Loop-Free Alternate (LFA) Fast Reroute (FRR) -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8938.xml"/>
<!--   Deterministic Networking (DetNet) Data Plane Framework -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8175.xml"/>
 <!--    Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol  -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-panrg-path-properties.xml"/>

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless.xml"/>
<!-- IPv6 Neighbor Discovery on Wireless Networks -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework.xml"/>


    <reference anchor="NASA" target="https://kscddms.ksc.nasa.gov/Reliability/Documents/150814-3bWhatIsReliability.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>RELIABILITY: Definition &amp; Quantitative Illustration</title>
        <author  initials="T." surname="Adams" fullname="Tim Adams" >
          <organization>NASA</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <!--Informative References-->
    </references>
    </references>


  </back>
</rfc>
