<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<!-- Compiles with XML2RFC v3 https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/cgi-bin/xml2rfc-dev.cgi -->

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-pthubert-raw-architecture-09"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RAW Architecture/Framework">Reliable and Available Wireless Architecture/Framework</title>
    <author initials="P" surname="Thubert" fullname="Pascal Thubert" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
      <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Building D</street>
      <street>45 Allee des Ormes - BP1200 </street>
      <city>MOUGINS - Sophia Antipolis</city>
      <code>06254</code>
      <country>France</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+33 497 23 26 34</phone>
    <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="G.Z." surname="Papadopoulos" fullname="Georgios Z. Papadopoulos">
      <organization>IMT Atlantique</organization>
      <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Office B00 - 114A</street>
      <street>2 Rue de la Chataigneraie</street>
      <city>Cesson-Sevigne - Rennes</city>
      <code>35510</code>
      <country>France</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+33 299 12 70 04</phone>
    <email>georgios.papadopoulos@imt-atlantique.fr</email>
      </address>
    </author>



    <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
       <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
       <address>
    <postal>
       <street/><city/>
       <region></region>
       <code/>
        <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
      <phone/>
      <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
       </address>
      </author>


    <date/>
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>RAW</workgroup>
    <keyword>Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
      <!--
      Due to uncontrolled interferences, including the self-induced multipath fading, deterministic networking can only be approached on wireless links. The radio conditions may change -way- faster than a centralized routing can adapt and reprogram, in particular when the controller is distant and connectivity is slow and limited. RAW separates the routing time scale at which a complex path is recomputed from the forwarding time scale at which the forwarding decision is taken for an individual packet. RAW operates at the forwarding time scale. The RAW problem is to decide, within the redundant solutions that are proposed by the routing, which will be used for each individual packet to provide a DetNet service while minimizing the waste of resources.
       !-->

      Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) provides for high
      reliability and availability for IP connectivity over a
      wireless medium. The wireless medium presents significant
      challenges to achieve deterministic properties such as low
      packet error rate, bounded consecutive losses, and bounded
      latency. This document defines the RAW Architecture.  It
      builds on the DetNet Architecture and discusses specific
      challenges and technology considerations needed to deliver
      DetNet service utilizing scheduled wireless segments and
      other media, e.g., frequency/time-sharing physical media
      resources with stochastic traffic.

      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>
   Deterministic Networking is an attempt to emulate the properties of a serial
   link over a switched fabric, by providing a bounded latency and eliminating
   congestion loss, even when co-existing with best-effort traffic.
   It is getting traction in various industries including professional A/V,
   manufacturing, online gaming, and smartgrid automation, enabling cost and
   performance optimizations (e.g., vs. loads of P2P cables).
      </t>
      <t>
   Bringing determinism in a packet network means eliminating the statistical
   effects of multiplexing that result in probabilistic jitter and loss.
   This can be approached with a tight control of the physical resources to
   maintain the amount of traffic within a budgetted volume of data per unit of
   time that fits the physical capabilities of the underlying network, and
   the use of time-shared resources (bandwidth and buffers) per circuit, and/or
   by shaping and/or scheduling the packets at every hop.
   </t>
   <t>
   This innovation was initially introduced on wired networks, with IEEE 802.1
   Time Sensitive networking (TSN) - for Ethernet LANs - and IETF DetNet.
   But the wired and the wireless media are fundamentally different at the
   physical level and in the possible abstractions that can be built for IP
   <xref target="I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless" format="default"/>.
   Wireless networks operate on a shared medium where uncontrolled interference,
   including the self-induced multipath fading, cause random transmission losses
   and add new dimensions to the statistical effects that affect reachability
   and packet delivery.
      </t>
      <t>
   To defeat those additional causes of transmission delay and loss,
   Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) leverages scheduled transmissions with
   redundancy and diversity in the spatial, time, code, and frequency domains.
   The challenge is to provide enough diversity and redundancy to ensure the
   timely packet delivery while preserving energy and optimizing the use of the
   shared spectrum.
   </t>
   <t>
   While the generic <xref target="RFC8557">"Deterministic Networking
   Problem Statement"</xref> applies to both the wired and the wireless media,
   the methods to achieve RAW must extend those used to support time-sensitive
   networking over wires, as a RAW solution has to address less consistent
   transmissions, energy conservation and shared spectrum efficiency.
   </t>
   <t>
   Uncontrolled interference and transmission obstacles may impede the wireless
   transmission, causing rapid variations of the throughput and packet delivery
   ratio (PDR) of the link. This uncertainty limits the volume and/or duration
   of traffic that can be safely transmitted on the same link while conforming
   to a RAW Service Level Agreement (SLA).
      </t>
      <t>

   This increased complexity explains why the development of deterministic
   wireless technologies has been lagging behind the similar efforts for wired systems, both at the IEEE and the IETF. But recent progress on scheduled
   radios such as TSCH and OFDMA indicates that wireless is finally catching up
   at the lower layers. Sitting at the layer above,
   RAW takes up the challenge of providing highly available and reliable
   end-to-end performances in a network with scheduled wireless segments.

      </t>
      <t>
   RAW provides DetNet elements that are specialized for short range radios.
   From this inheritance, RAW stays agnostic to the radio
   layer underneath though the capability to schedule transmissions is assumed.
   How the PHY is programmed to do so, and whether the radio is single-hop
   or meshed, are unknown at the IP layer and not part of the RAW abstraction.

      </t>
      <t>
   The <xref target="RFC8655">"Deterministic Networking Architecture"</xref> is
   composed of three planes: the Application (User) Plane, the Controller Plane,
   and the Network Plane. The RAW Architecture extends the DetNet Network Plane,
   to accomodate one or multiple hops of homogeneous or heterogeneous wireless
   technologies, e.g. a Wi-Fi6 Mesh or parallel CBRS access links federated by a
   5G backhaul.
      </t>

      <t>
   The establishment of a path is not in-scope for RAW. It may be the product of
   a centralized Controller Plane as described for DetNet. As opposed to wired
   networks, the action of installing a path over a set of wireless links
   may be very slow relative to the speed at which the radio conditions vary,
   and it makes sense in the wireless case to provide redundant forwarding
   solutions along a complex path and to leave it to the Network Plane to
   select which of those forwarding solutions are to be used for a given packet
   based on the current conditions.
      </t>
      <t>
   RAW distinguishes the longer time scale at which routes are computed from the
   the shorter forwarding time scale where per-packet decisions are made.
   RAW operates within the Network Plane at the forwarding time scale on one
   DetNet flow over a complex path called a Track. The Track is preestablished
   and installed by means outside of the scope of RAW; it may be strict or loose depending on whether each or just a subset of the hops are observed and
   controlled by RAW.
      </t>
      <t>
   The RAW Architecture covers Network Plane protocol elements such as
   Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) to observe some or all hops along a Track as well as the end-to-end packet delivery, and in-band control
   to optimize the use of redundancy to achieve the required SLA with minimal
   use of constrained resources.
      </t>

    </section>
    <!-- Introduction -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>The RAW problem</name>

   <section anchor="terms" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>

    <t>RAW reuses terminology defined for DetNet in the <xref target="RFC8655">
    "Deterministic Networking Architecture"</xref>, e.g., PREOF for Packet
    Replication, Elimination and Ordering Functions.
    </t><t>
    RAW also reuses terminology defined for 6TiSCH in <xref target=
    "RFC9030" format="default"/> such as the term Track.
    A Track as a complex path with associated PAREO operations. The concept is
    abstract to the underlaying technology and applies to any fully or partially
    wireless mesh, including, e.g., a Wi-Fi mesh.
    RAW specifies strict and loose Tracks depending on whether the path is fully
    controlled by RAW or traverses an opaque network where RAW cannot observe
    and control the individual hops.
    </t><t>
    RAW uses the following terminology:
    </t>
    <dl>
    <dt>PAREO:</dt><dd>Packet (hybrid) ARQ, Replication, Elimination and
    Ordering. PAREO is a superset Of DetNet's PREOF that includes
    radio-specific techniques such as short range broadcast, MUMIMO,
    constructive interference and overhearing, which can be
    leveraged separately or combined to increase the reliability.
    </dd>
    <dt>Flow:</dt><dd>A collection of consecutive packets that must be placed
    on the same Track to receive an equivalent treatment from Ingress to Egress
    within the Track. Multiple flows may be transported along the same Track.
    The subTrack that is selected for the flow may change over time under the
    control of the PSE.
    </dd>
    <dt>Track:</dt><dd>
    <t>A networking graph that can be used as a "path" to transport RAW packets
    with equivalent treatment; as opposed to the usual understanding of a path
    (see for instance the definition of "path" in section 1.1 of <xref target=
    "RFC9049"/>), a Track may fork and rejoin to enable the PAREO operations.
    </t>
    <t>
    In DetNet <xref target="RFC8655"/> terms, a Track has the following
    properties:
    </t>
    <ul>
    <li>
    A Track has one Ingress and one Egress nodes, which operate as DetNet Edge
    nodes.
    </li><li>
    A Track is reversible, meaning that packets can be routed against the flow
    of data packets, e.g., to carry OAM measurements or control messages back to
    the Ingress.
    </li><li>
    The vertices of the Track are DetNet Relay nodes that operate at the DetNet Service sublayer and provide the PAREO functions.
    </li><li>
    The topological edges of the graph are serial sequences of DetNet Transit
    nodes that operate at the DetNet Forwarding sublayer.
    </li>
    </ul>
    </dd>
    <dt>SubTrack:</dt><dd>A Track within a Track. The RAW PSE selects a subTrack
    on a per-packet or a per-collection of packets basis to provide the desired reliability for the transported flows.
    </dd>
    <dt>Segment:</dt><dd>A serial path formed by a topological edge of a Track.
    East-West Segments are oriented from Ingress (East) to Egress (West).
    North/South Segments can be bidirectional; to avoid loops, measures must be
    taken to ensure that a given packet flows either Northwards or Southwards
    along a bidirectional Segment, but never bounces back.
    </dd>
    <dt>Flapping:</dt><dd>In the context of RAW, a link flaps when the
    reliability of the wireless connectivity drops abruptly for a short
    period of time, typically of a subsecond to seconds duration.
    </dd>

    <dt>AOM:</dt> <dd>
    OAM stands for Operations, Administration, and Maintenance, and covers
    the processes, activities, tools, and standards involved with operating,
    administering, managing and maintaining any system. This document uses the
    terms Operations, Administration, and Maintenance, in conformance with the
    IETF <xref target="RFC6291">'Guidelines for the Use of the "OAM" Acronym
    in the IETF'</xref> and the system observed by the RAW OAM is the Track.
    </dd>
    <dt>Active OAM:</dt> <dd>Active OAM uses specially constructed test packets
    crafted to observe a particular Track, subTrack, or Segment of a Track.
    </dd>
    <dt>In-Band OAM:</dt><dd>
    An active OAM packet is considered in-band in the monitored Track when it
    traverses the same set of links and interfaces receiving the same QoS and
    PAREO treatment as the data flows that are injected in the Track.
    </dd>
    <dt>Out-of-Band OAM:</dt><dd>
    An active OAM packet is out-of-band if its datapath is topologically the
    same as of that of the Track, subTrack or Segment being observed, but the
    QoS or PAREO treatment is different (e.g., lower CoS).
    </dd>
    <dt>Limited OAM:</dt><dd>
    An active OAM packet is a Limited OAM packet when it is observes the RAW
    operation over a node, a segment, or a subTrack of the Track, though not
    from Ingress to Egress. It is injected in the datapath and extracted from
    the datapath around the particular function or subnetwork (e.g., around a
    relay providing a service layer replication point) that is being tested.
    </dd>
    <dt>Reverse OAM:</dt><dd>
    A Reverse OAM packet is an Out-of-Band OAM packet that traverses the Track
    from West to East and North-South in one of either direction, to capture and
    report OAM measurements upstream.
    </dd>

    </dl>

    <t>
    In the context of the RAW work, Reliability and Availability are defined as
    follows:
    </t>
    <dl>
    <dt>Reliability:</dt><dd>Reliability is a measure of the probability
    that an item will perform its intended function for a specified
    interval under stated conditions. For RAW, the service that is expected
    is delivery within a bounded latency and a failure is when the packet
    is either lost or delivered too late.  RAW expresses reliability in
    terms of Mean Time Between Failure (MTBF) and Maximum Consecutive
    Failures (MCF). More in <xref target="NASA"/>.</dd>
    <dt>Availability:</dt><dd>Availability is a measure of the relative
    amount of time where a path operates in stated condition, in other words
    (uptime)/(uptime+downtime). Because a serial wireless path may not be
    good enough to provide the required reliability, and even 2 parallel
    paths may not be over a longer period of time, the RAW availability
    implies a path that is a lot more complex than what DetNet typically
    envisages (a Track).
    </dd>
    <dt>Residence Time:</dt><dd>A residence time (RT) is defined as the
    time period between the reception of a packet starts and the
    transmission of the packet begins. In the context of RAW, RT is useful
    for a transit node, not ingress or egress.</dd>
    </dl>
    </section>
    <!-- Terminology -->
    <!--  1111111111111111    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliability and Availability</name>


    <!--  2222222222222222    -->
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>High Availability Engineering Principles</name>

    <t>
    The reliability criteria of a critical system pervade through its elements,
    and if the system comprises a data network then the data network is also
    subject to the inherited reliability and availability criteria.
    It is only natural to consider the art of high availability engineering and
    apply it to wireless communications in the context of RAW.
    </t>

    <t>
    There are three principles [pillars] of high availability engineering:
    </t>
     <ol spacing="compact">
     <li>elimination of single points of failure</li>
     <li>reliable crossover</li>
     <li>prompt detection of failures as they occur.</li>
     </ol>
     <t>
     These principles are common to all high availability systems, not just ones
     with Internet technology at the center.  Examples of both non-Internet and
     Internet are included.
    </t>


    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Elimination of Single Points of Failure</name>

    <t>
    Physical and logical components in a system happen to fail, either as the
    effect of wear and tear, when used beyond acceptable limits, or due to a
    software bug.
    It is necessary to decouple component failure from system failure to avoid
    the latter.
    This allows failed components to be restored while the rest of the system
    continues to function.
    </t>
    <t>
    IP Routers leverage routing protocols to compute alternate routes in case
    of a failure. There is a rather open-ended issue over alternate routes --
    for example, when links are cabled through the same conduit, they form a
    shared risk link group (SRLG), and will share the same fate if the bundle is
    cut. The same effect can happen with virtual links that end up in a same physical transport through the games of encapsulation. In a same fashion,
    an interferer or an obstacle may affect multiple wireless transmissions at
    the same time, even between different sets of peers.
    </t>
    <t>
    Intermediate network Nodes such as routers, switches and APs, wire bundles
    and the air medium itself can become single points of failure. For High
    Availability, it is thus required to use physically link- and Node-disjoint
    paths; in the wireless space, it is also required to use the highest
    possible degree of diversity in the transmissions over the air to combat the
    additional causes of transmission loss.
    </t>
    <t>
    From an economics standpoint, executing this principle properly generally
    increases capitalization expense because of the redundant equipment. In a
    constrained network where the waste of energy and bandwidth should be
    minimized, an excessive use of redundant links must be avoided; for RAW this
    means that the extra bandwidth must be used wisely and with parcimony.
    </t>

    </section>
      <!--Elimination of Single Points of Failure-->



    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliable Crossover</name>

    <t>
    Having a backup equipment has a limited value unless it can be reliably switched into use within the down-time parameters.
    IP Routers execute reliable crossover continuously because
    the routers will use any alternate routes that are available <xref target=
    "RFC0791"/>. This is due to the stateless nature of IP datagrams and the
    dissociation of the datagrams from the forwarding routes they take.
    The <xref target="RFC5714">"IP Fast Reroute Framework"</xref> analyzes
    mechanisms for fast failure detection and path repair for IP Fast-Reroute,
    and discusses the case of multiple failures and SRLG. Examples of FRR
    techniques include Remote Loop-Free Alternate <xref target="RFC7490"/> and
    backup label-switched path (LSP) tunnels for the local repair of LSP tunnels
    using RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC4090"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
    Deterministic flows, on the contrary, are attached to specific paths where
    dedicated resources are reserved for each flow. This is why each DetNet path
    must inherently provide sufficient redundancy to provide the guaranteed SLA
    at all times.
    The DetNet PREOF typically leverages 1+1 redundancy whereby a packet is sent
    twice, over non-congruent paths. This avoids the gap during the fast reroute
    operation, but doubles the traffic in the network.
    </t>
    <t>
    In the case of RAW, the expectation is that multiple transient faults may
    happen in overlapping time windows, in which case the 1+1 redundancy with
    delayed reestablishment of the second path will not provide the required
    guarantees.
    The Data Plane must be configured with a sufficient degree of
    redundancy to select an alternate redundant path immediately upon a fault,
    without the need for a slow intervention from the controller plane.
    </t>
    </section>
      <!--Reliable Crossover-->





    <!--  333333333333333333333   -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Prompt Notification of Failures</name>
    <t>
    The execution of the two above principles is likely to render a system where
    the user will rarely see a failure. But someone needs to in order to direct
    maintenance.
    </t>
    <t>
    There are many reasons for system monitoring (FCAPS for fault, configuration,
    accounting, performance, security is a handy mental checklist) but fault
    monitoring is sufficient reason.
    </t>
    <t>
    <xref target="RFC3411">"An Architecture for Describing
    Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks"</xref>
    describes how to use SNMP to observe and correct long-term faults.
    </t>
    <t>
    <xref target="RFC3272">
    "Overview and Principles of Internet Traffic Engineering"</xref> discusses
    the importance of measurement for network protection, and provides abstract
    an method for network survivability with the analysis of a traffic matrix
    as observed by SNMP, probing techniques, FTP, IGP link state advertisements,
    and more.
    </t>

    <t>
    Those measurements are needed in the context of RAW to inform the controller
    and make the long term reactive decision to rebuild a complex  path. But RAW
    itself operates in the Network Plane at a faster time scale. To act on the
    Data Plane, RAW needs live information from the Operational Plane , e.g.,
    using <xref target="RFC5880">Bidirectional Forwarding Detection</xref>
    and its variants (bidirectional and remote BFD) to protect a link, and
    OAM techniques to protect a path.
    </t>

<!--

    Security requirements. SNMP messages need to be authentic in all cases.
    Implementations may need to be confidential as well.



[ ... dovetail this into the OAM things that need to be included. Most of the discussion seems to cluster around performance management]

-->
    </section>
      <!--Prompt Notification of Failures-->




   </section>
      <!--Reliability Engineering-->
    <!--  22222222222222222222    -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Applying Reliability Concepts to Networking</name>
    <t>
    The terms Reliability and Availability are defined for use in RAW in
    <xref target="terms"/> and the reader is invited to read
    <xref target="NASA"/>
    for more details on the general definition of Reliability.
    Practically speaking a number of nines is often used to indicate the
    reliability of a data link, e.g., 5 nines indicate a
    Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR) of 99.999%.
    </t>
    <t>
    This number is typical in a wired
    environment where the loss is due to a random event such as a solar particle
    that affects the transmission of a particular frame, but does not affect the
    previous or next frame, nor frames transmitted on other links. Note that the
    QoS requirements in RAW may include a bounded latency, and a packet that
    arrives too late is a fault and not considered as delivered.
    </t>
    <t>
    For a periodic networking pattern such as an automation control loop, this
    number is proportional to the Mean Time Between Failures (MTBF).
    When a single fault can have dramatic consequences, the MTBF expresses the
    chances that the unwanted fault event occurs. In data networks,
    this is rarely the case. Packet loss cannot never be fully avoided and the
    systems are built to resist to one loss, e.g., using redundancy with Retries
    (HARQ) or Packet Replication and Elimination (PRE), or, in a typical control
    loop, by linear interpolation from the previous measurements.
    </t>
   <t>
    But the linear interpolation method cannot resist multiple consecutive
    losses, and a high MTBF is desired as a guarantee that this will not happen,
    IOW that the number of losses-in-a-row can be bounded. In that case, what is
    really desired is a Maximum Consecutive Failures (MCF).
    If the number of losses in a row passes the MCF, the control loop has to
    abort and the system, e.g., the production line, may need to enter an
    emergency stop condition.
    </t>
   <t>
    Engineers that build automated processes may use the network reliability
    expressed in nines or as an MTBF as a proxy to indicate an MCF, e.g., as
    described in section 7.4 of the <xref target="RFC8578">"Deterministic
    Networking Use Cases"</xref>.
    </t>
    </section>
      <!--Applying Reliability concepts to Networking-->
    <!--  22222222222222222222    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Reliability in the Context of RAW</name>
    <t>
    In contrast with wired networks, errors in transmission are the predominant
    source of packet loss in wireless networks.
    </t>
    <t>
    The root cause for the loss may be of multiple origins, calling for
    the use of different forms of diversity:
    </t>
    <dl>
    <dt>Multipath Fading:</dt><dd>
    <t>A destructive interference by a reflection of the original signal.
    </t>
    <t>A radio signal may be received directly
    (line-of-sight) and/or as a reflection on a physical structure (echo).
    The reflections take a longer path and are delayed by the extra distance
    divided by the speed of light in the medium. Depending on the frequency, the
    echo lands with a different phase which may add up to (constructive
    interference) or cancel the direct signal (destructive interference).
    </t>
    <t>
    The affected frequencies depend on the relative position of the sender, the
    receiver, and all the reflecting objects in the environment.
    A given hop will suffer from multipath fading for multiple packets in a
    row till the something moves that changes the reflection patterns.
    </t>
    </dd>
    <dt>Co-channel Interference:</dt><dd>
    <t>
    Energy in the spectrum used for the transmission confuses the receiver.
    </t>
    <t>
    The wireless medium itself is a Shared Risk Link Group (SRLG) for nearby
    users of the same spectrum, as an interference may affect multiple co-channel
    transmissions between different peers within the interference domain of the
    interferer, possibly even when they use different technologies.
    </t>
    </dd>
    <dt>Obstacle in Fresnel Zone:</dt><dd>
    <t>
    The optimal transmission happens when the Fresnel Zone between the sender
    and the receiver is free of obstacles.
    </t>
    <t>
    As long as a physical object (e.g., a metallic trolley between peers) that
    affects the transmission is not removed, the quality of the link is affected.
    </t>
    </dd>
    </dl>
    <t>
    In an environment that is rich of metallic structures and mobile objects, a
    single radio link will provide a fuzzy service, meaning that it cannot be trusted to transport the traffic reliably over a long period of time.
    </t>
    <t>
    Transmission losses are typically not independent, and their nature and
    duration are unpredictable; as long as a physical object (e.g., a metallic
    trolley between peers) that affects the transmission is not removed, or as
    long as the interferer (e.g., a radar) keeps transmitting, a continuous
    stream of packets will be affected.
    </t>
    <t>
    The key technique to combat those unpredictable losses is diversity.
    Different forms of diversity are necessary to combat different causes of
    loss and the use of diversity must be maximised to optimize the PDR.
    </t>
    <t>
    A single packet may be sent at different times (time diversity) over diverse
    paths (spatial diversity) that rely on diverse radio channels (frequency
    diversity) and diverse PHY technologies, e.g., narrowband vs. spread
    spectrum, or diverse codes.
    Using time diversity will defeat short-term interferences;
    spatial diversity combats very local causes such as multipath fading;
    narrowband and spread spectrum are relatively innocuous to one another and
    can be used for diversity in the presence of the other.
    </t>


    </section>
      <!--Reliability in the Context of RAW-->

    </section>
    <!--Reliability and Availability-->
    <!--  11111111111111111111    -->



    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Use Cases and Requirements Served</name>
        <t>
   In order to focus on real-worlds issues and assert the feasibility of
   the proposed capabilities, RAW focuses on selected technologies that can
   be scheduled at the lower layers: IEEE Std. 802.15.4 timeslotted channel
   hopping (TSCH), 3GPP 5G ultra-reliable low latency communications (URLLC),
   IEEE 802.11ax/be where 802.11be is extreme high throughput (EHT), and L-band
   Digital Aeronautical  Communications System (LDACS).
   See <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies" format="default"/> for more.

      </t>
      <t>
    <xref target="RFC8578" format="default">"Deterministic Networking Use Cases"
    </xref> presents a number of wireless use cases including Wireless, such as
    application to Industrial Applications, Pro-Audio, and SmartGrid Automation.
   <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases" format="default"/> adds a number
   of use cases that demonstrate the need for RAW capabilities for new
   applications such as Pro-Gaming and drones.
   The use cases can be abstracted in two families, Loose Protection, e.g.,
   protecting the first hop in Radio Access Protection and Strict Protection,
   e.g., providing End-to-End Protection in a wireless mesh.
      </t>




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Radio Access Protection</name>

<t>
    To maintain the required SLA at all times, a wireless Host
    may use more than one Radio Access Network (RAN) in parallel.
</t>

<figure anchor="Figranp">
          <name>Radio Access Protection</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
                                   ...   ..
                 RAN 1  -----  ...     ..  ...
              /              .      ..         ....
+--------+  /              .                    ....    +-----------+
|Wireless|-                .                     .....  |  Service  |
| Device |-***-- RAN 2 -- .       Internet       ....---|     /     |
|(STA/UE)|-                ..                   .....   |Application|
+--------+  $$$             .               .......     +-----------+
              \               ...   ...     .....
                 RAN n  --------  ...   .....

*** = flapping at this time  $$$ expensive
       </artwork>
</figure>
<t>
    The RANs may be heterogeneous, e.g.,
    3GPP 5G <xref target="I-D.farkas-raw-5g"/> and
    Wi-Fi <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"/> for high-speed
    communication, in which case a Layer-3 abstraction becomes useful to select
    which of the RANs are used at a particular point of time, and the amount of
    traffic that is distributed over each RAN.
</t>
<t>
    The idea is that the rest of the path to the destination(s) is protected
    separately (e.g., uses non-congruent paths, leverages DetNet / TSN, etc...)
    and is a lot more reliable, e.g., wired. In that case, RAW observes the
    reliability of the end-to-end operation through each of the RANs but only
    observes and controls the wireless operation the first hop.
</t>
<t> A variation of that use case has a pair of wireless Hosts connected over a
    wired core / backbone network. In that case, RAW observes and
    controls the Ingress and Egress RANs, while neglecting the hops in the core.
    The resulting loose Track may be instantiated, e.g., using tunneling or
    loose source routing between the RANs.
</t>


    </section>
    <!--Radio Access Protection-->



    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>End-to-End Protection in a Wireless Mesh</name>

<t>
    In radio technologies that support mesh networking (e.g., Wi-Fi and TSCH),
    a Track is a complex path with distributed PAREO capabilities. In that case,
    RAW operates through the multipath and makes decisions either at the Ingress
    or at every hop (more in <xref target="trk"/>).
</t>
       <figure anchor="Figtrk">
          <name>End-to-End Protection</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
         A-------B-------C-----D
        /  \   /       /        \
 Ingress ----M-------N--zzzzz--- Egress
        \      \   /            /
         P--zzz--Q-------------R

zzz = flapping now
       </artwork>
       </figure>
       <t>The Protection may be imposed by the source based on end-to-end OAM,
       or performed hop-by-hop, in which case the OAM must enables the
       intermediate Nodes to estimate the quality of the rest of the feasible
       paths in the remainder of the Track to the destination.
       </t>
    </section>
    <!--End-to-End Protection in a Wireless Mesh-->



    </section>
    <!-- Use Cases and Requirements Served -->


    <!--  1111111111111111111111111111   -->



    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Related Work at The IETF</name>
      <t>RAW intersects with protocols or practices in development at the IETF
      as follows:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
    <li>
      The Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP)
      <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> from
      <xref target="MANET" format="default"/> can be leveraged at each hop
      to derive generic radio metrics (e.g., based on LQI, RSSI, queueing delays
      and ETX) on individual hops.
      </li>
    <li>
      <xref target="detnet" format="default"/> provides an OAM framework with
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework" format="default"/> that
      applies within the DetNet dataplane described in
      <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>,which is typically based on
      MPLS or IPv6 pseudowires.

      </li>
    <li>
      <xref target="BFD" format="default"/> detect faults in the path between an
      Ingress and an Egress forwarding engines, but is unaware of the complexity
      of a path with replication, and expects bidirectionality.
      BFD asynchronous mode considers delivery as success whereas with DetNet
      and RAW, the bounded latency can be as important as the delivery itself,
      and delivering too late is actually a failure. Note that the
      BFD Demand mode with unsolicited notifications may be more suitable then
      the Asynchronous BFD mode. The use of the Demand mode in MPLS is analyzed
      in <xref target="I-D.mirsky-bfd-mpls-demand" format="default"/> and
      similar considerations could apply to IP as well.
      </li>
    <li>
      <xref target="SPRING" format="default"/> and
      <xref target="BIER" format="default"/> define in-band
      signaling that influences the routing when decided at the head-end on the
      path. There's already one RAW-related draft at BIER
      <xref target="I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination" format="default"/>
      more may follow.
      RAW will need new in-band signaling when the decision is distributed,
      e.g., required chances of reliable delivery to destination within latency.
      This signaling enables relays to tune retries and replication to meet the required SLA.
      </li>
    <li>
      <xref target="CCAMP" format="default"/> defines protocol-independent
      metrics and parameters
      (measurement attributes) for describing links and paths that are required
      for routing and signaling in technology-specific networks. RAW would be a
      source of requirements for CCAMP to define metrics that are significant to
      the focus radios.
      </li>
     <li>
      <xref target="IPPM" format="default"/> develops and maintains standard
      metrics that can be applied to the quality, performance, and reliability
      of Internet data delivery services and applications running over transport
      layer protocols (e.g. TCP, UDP) over IP.
      </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <!--Related Work at The IETF   -->
    <!--  1111111111111111111   -->

    </section>      <!-- The RAW problem -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

    <section anchor="frame" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>The RAW Framework</name>


    <!--  1111111111111111111111111111   -->


    <section  anchor="scope" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Scope and Prerequisites</name>
      <t>
   A prerequisite to the RAW operation is that an end-to-end routing function
   computes a complex sub-topology along which forwarding can happen between a
   source and one or more destinations. The concept of Track is specified in the
   <xref target="RFC9030" format="default">
   6TiSCH Architecture</xref> to represent that complex sub-topology. Tracks
   provide a high degree of redundancy and diversity and enable the DetNet
   PREOF, network coding, and possibly RAW specific techniques such as PAREO,
   leveraging frequency diversity, time diversity, and possibly other forms of
   diversity as well.
      </t>
      <t>
   How the routing operation (e.g., PCE) in the Controller Plane computes the
   Track is out of scope for RAW. The scope of the RAW operation is one Track,
   and the goal of the RAW operation is to optimize the use of the Track at the
   forwarding timescale to maintain the expected SLA while optimizing the usage
   of constrained resources such as energy and spectrum.
      </t>
      <t>
   Another prerequisite is that an IP link can be established over the radio
   with some guarantees in terms of service reliability, e.g., it can be relied
   upon to transmit a packet within a bounded latency and provides a guaranteed
   BER/PDR outside rare but existing transient outage windows that can last from
   split  seconds to minutes. The radio layer can be programmed with abstract
   parameters, and can return an abstract view of the state of the Link to help
   the Network Layer forwarding decision (think DLEP from MANET).
      </t>
      <t>
   How the radio interface manages its lower layers is out of control and out of
   scope for RAW. In the same fashion, the non-RAW portion along a loose Track
   is by definition out of control and out of scope for RAW. Whether it is a
   single hop or a mesh is also unknown and out of scope.
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- Prerequisites -->
    <!--  111111111111111111    -->
    <!--  111111111111111111111    -->

    <section anchor="timescale" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Routing Time Scale vs. Forwarding Time Scale</name>
      <t>
   With DetNet, the Controller Plane Function that handles the routing computation and maintenance (the PCE) can be centralized and can
   reside outside the network.
   In a wireless mesh, the path to the PCE can be expensive and slow,
   possibly going across the whole mesh and back.
   Reaching to the PCE can also be slow in regards to the speed
   of events that affect the forwarding operation at the radio layer.

      </t><t>
   Due to that cost and latency, the Controller Plane is not
   expected to be sensitive/reactive to transient changes. The abstraction of a
   link at the routing level is expected to use statistical metrics
   that aggregate the behavior of a link over long periods of time, and
   represent its properties as shades of gray as opposed to numerical values
   such as a link quality indicator, or a boolean value for either up or down.
      </t>

         <figure anchor="Figcontrol">
          <name>Time Scales</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
       <![CDATA[
               +----------------+
               |  Controller    |
               |    [PCE]       |
               +----------------+
                       ^
                       |
                      Slow
                       |
   _-._-._-._-._-._-.  |  ._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
 _-._-._-._-._-._-._-. | _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
                       |
                    Expensive
                       |
                ....   |  .......
            ....    .  | .       .......
         ....          v               ...
       ..    A-------B-------C---D        ..
    ...     /  \   /       /      \      ..
   .       I ----M-------N--***-- E        ..
   ..       \      \   /         /         ...
     ..      P--***--Q----------R        ....
       ..                              ....
        .   <----- Fast ------->    ....
         .......                ....
                .................

*** = flapping at this time
    ]]>
       </artwork>
       </figure>
      <t>
   In the case of wireless, the changes that affect the forwarding decision can
   happen frequently and often for short durations, e.g., a mobile object moves
   between a transmitter and a receiver, and will cancel the line of sight
   transmission for a few seconds, or a radar measures the depth of a pool and
   interferes on a particular channel for a split second.
      </t>
      <t>
   There is thus a desire to separate the long term computation of the route and
   the short term forwarding decision. In that model, the routing operation
   computes a complex Track that enables multiple Non-Equal Cost Multi-Path
   (N-ECMP) forwarding solutions, and leaves it to the Data Plane to make
   the per-packet decision of which of these possibilities should be used.
      </t>
      <t>
   In the wired world, and more specifically in the context of Traffic
   Engineering (TE), an alternate path can be used upon the detection of a
   failure in the main path, e.g., using OAM in MPLS-TP or BFD over a
   collection of SD-WAN tunnels. RAW
   formalizes a forwarding time scale that is an order(s) of magnitude shorter
   than the controller plane routing time scale, and separates the protocols
   and metrics that are used at both scales.
   Routing can operate on long term statistics such as delivery
   ratio over minutes to hours, but as a first approximation can ignore flapping.
   On the other hand, the RAW forwarding decision is made at the scale of the packet rate, and uses information that must be pertinent at the present time for the current transmission(s).
      </t>

    </section >
    <!--Routing Time Scale vs. Forwarding Time Scale-->

    <!--  11111111111111111111    -->


    <section anchor="trk" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Wireless Tracks</name>
   <t>
    The  <xref target="RFC9030">"6TiSCH Architecture"</xref>
    introduces the concept of Track. RAW extends the concept to any wireless mesh
    technology, including, e.g., Wi-Fi.
    A simple Track is composed of a direct sequence of reserved hops to ensure
    the transmission of a single packet from a source Node to a destination Node
    across a multihop path.
    </t>
    <t>
    A Complex Track provides multiple N-ECMP forwarding solutions. The Complex
    Track enables to support multi-path redundant forwarding
    by employing PRE functions <xref target="RFC8655"/> and the ingress and
    within the Track.
    For example, a Complex Track  may branch off and rejoin over non-congruent
    segments.
    </t>
    <t>
    In the context of RAW, some links or segments in the Track may be reversible,
    meaning that they can be used in either direction. In that case, an indication
    in the packet signals the direction of the reversible links or segments that
    the packet traverses and thus places a constraint that prevents loops from
    occuring. An indidual packet follows a destination-oriented directed acyclic
    graph (DODAG) towards a destination Node inside the Complex Track.
    </t>

</section>
<!--Wireless Tracks-->

    <!--  11111111111111111    -->
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>PAREO Functions</name>
      <t>
    RAW may control whether and how to use packet replication and elimination
    (PRE), Automatic Repeat reQuest (ARQ), Hybrid ARQ (HARQ) that includes
    Forward Error Correction (FEC) and coding, and other wireless-specific
    techniques such as overhearing and constructive interferences, in order to
    increase the reliabiility and availability of the end-to-end transmission.
    </t>
    <t>
    Collectively, those function are called PAREO for Packet (hybrid) ARQ, Replication, Elimination and Ordering. By tuning dynamically the use of
    PAREO functions, RAW avoids the waste of critical resources such as spectrum
    and energy while providing that the guaranteed SLA, e.g., by adding redundancy only when a spike of loss is observed.
    </t>
    <t>
    In a nutshell, PAREO establishes several paths in a
    network to provide redundancy and parallel transmissions to
    bound the end-to-end delay to traverse the network.
    Optionally, promiscuous listening between paths is possible, such that the Nodes
    on one path may overhear transmissions along the other path.
    Considering the scenario shown in <xref target="fig_ladder"/>, many
    different paths are possible for to traverse the network from ingress to
    egress. A simple way to benefit from this topology could be to use the
    two independent paths via Nodes A, C, E and via B, D, F.  But
    more complex paths are possible by interleaving transmissions
    from the lower level of the path to the upper level.
    </t>



      <figure anchor="fig_ladder" align="center" title="A Ladder Shape with Two Parallel Paths">
     <artwork align="center">

           (A) -- (C) -- (E)
         /                   \
Ingress =   |      |      |   = Egress
         \                   /
           (B) -- (D) -- (F)

</artwork>
     </figure>
    <t>
     PAREO may also take advantage of
     the shared properties of the wireless medium to compensate for the
     potential loss that is incurred with radio transmissions.
    </t>
    <t>
     For instance, when the source sends to Node A, Node B may listen
     promiscuously and get a second chance to receive the frame without an
     additional transmission. Note that B would not have to listen if it
     already received that particular frame at an earlier timeslot in a dedicated transmission towards B.
<!-- [->] This is assuming some sort of implicit knowledge in B. Not sure if this is  -->
<!-- possible without specific signaling.   -->
<!-- [GP] Yes, we may need additional 6P transactions from the source to B, or  -->
<!-- multicast 6P transaction from the source to both A and B. However, this  -->
<!-- need to be discussed and defined. We have referred to these requirements in the "Requirements Related to Cell Reservation" section in the upcoming version.  (DONE) -->
    </t>


    <t>
    The PAREO model can be implemented in both centralized and distributed scheduling approaches.
    In the centralized approach, a Path Computation Element (PCE) scheduler calculates a Track and schedules the communication.
    In the distributed approach, the Track is computed within the network,
    and signaled in the packets, e.g., using BIER-TE, Segment Routing, or a  Source Routing Header.
    </t>



    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Packet Replication</name>

    <t>
    By employing a Packet Replication procedure, a Node forwards
    a copy of each data packet to more than one successor.
    To do so, each Node (i.e., Ingress and intermediate Node) sends the
    data packet multiple times as separate unicast transmissions.
    For instance, in <xref target="fig_replication"/>, the Ingress Node is
    transmitting the packet to both successors, nodes A and B, at two different
    times.
    </t>


    <figure anchor="fig_replication" align="center"
        title="Packet Replication">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

             ===> (A) => (C) => (E) ===
           //        \\//   \\//       \\
   Ingress           //\\   //\\          Egress
           \\       //  \\ //  \\      //
             ===> (B) => (D) => (F) ===

        ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
    <t>
    An example schedule is shown in <xref target="tab_replication_schedule"/>.
    This way, the transmission leverages with the time and spatial forms of diversity.
    </t>
    <table anchor="tab_replication_schedule"><name>Packet Replication: Sample schedule</name>
   <thead>
      <tr>
		   <th align='center'>Channel</th>
		   <th align='center'>0</th>
		   <th align='center'>1</th>
		   <th align='center'>2</th>
		   <th align='center'>3</th>
		   <th align='center'>4</th>
		   <th align='center'>5</th>
		   <th align='center'>6</th>
      </tr>

   </thead><tbody>

			<tr><td>0</td>
    			<td align='center'>S->A</td>
    			<td align='center'>S->B</td>
    			<td align='center'>B->C</td>
    			<td align='center'>B->D</td>
    			<td align='center'>C->F</td>
    			<td align='center'>E->R</td>
    			<td align='center'>F->R</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>1</td>
    			<td align='center'> </td>
    			<td align='center'>A->C</td>
    			<td align='center'>A->D</td>
    			<td align='center'>C->E</td>
    			<td align='center'>D->E</td>
    			<td align='center'>D->F</td>
    			<td align='center'> </td>
        </tr>

    </tbody>
    </table>


<!-- [XV] here you are only considering duplication at the source. While would be better IMHO to duplicate before those links that show lower performance. Would you also consider duplication at inner hops?  -->
<!-- [GP] Yes, definitely, there is replication (duplication) at inner hops.  -->
<!-- For instance, A will transmit both to its default parent C and alternative B. -->
<!-- The Figure 2 and the text in 4.1 is updated. (Modified, DONE) -->
<!-- As far as only duplicating at lower performance links, this is a very good point and a nice optimisation target. This needs to be discussed further -->

<!-- [GP] Do you think a Figure with the TSCH schedule representation would be helpful?     -->
<!-- [RK] Yes, I do. Added  fig_replication_schedule -->

</section>




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Packet Elimination</name>


    <t>
    The replication operation increases the traffic load in the
    network, due to packet duplications.  This may occur at several stages inside the Track, and to avoid an explosion of the number of copies, a Packet Elimination procedure must be applied as well. To this aim, once a Node receives the first copy of a data packet, it discards the subsequent copies.
    </t><t>
    The logical functions of Replication and Elimination may be collocated in an intermediate Node, the  Node first eliminating the redundant copies and then sending the packet exactly once to each of the selected successors.
    </t>

</section>




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Promiscuous Overhearing</name>



    <t>
    Considering that the wireless medium is broadcast by nature, any neighbor of
    a transmitter may overhear a transmission.
    By employing the Promiscuous Overhearing operation, the next hops have additional opportunities to capture the data packets.
    In <xref target="fig_overhearing"/>, when Node A is transmitting to its DP
    (Node C), the AP (Node D) and its sibling (Node B) may decode this data packet as
    well.
    As a result, by employing corellated paths, a Node may have multiple
    opportunities to receive a given data packet.
    <!--
    This feature not only enhances the end-to-end reliability but also it reduces the
    end-to-end delay and increases energy efficiency.
    -->
    </t>


    <figure anchor="fig_overhearing" align="center"
        title="Unicast with Overhearing">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

           ===> (A) ====> (C) ====> (E) ====
         //     ^ | \\                      \\
  Ingress       | |   \\                      Egress
         \\     | v     \\                  //
           ===> (B) ====> (D) ====> (F) ====

]]></artwork>
    </figure>


</section>






    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Constructive Interference</name>

<t>
    Constructive Interference can be seen as the reverse of Promiscuous
    Overhearing, and refers to the case where two senders transmit the exact
    same signal in a fashion that the emitted symbols add up at the receiver and
    permit a reception that would not be possible with a single sender at the
    same PHY mode and  the same power level.
</t><t>
    Constructive Interference was proposed on 5G, Wi-Fi7 and even tested on
    IEEE Std 802.14.5.  The hard piece is to synchronize the senders to the
    point that the signals are emitted at slightly different time to offset the
    difference of propagation delay that corresponds to the difference of
    distance of the transmitters to the receiver at the speed of light to the
    point that the symbols are superposed long enough to be recognizable.
</t>

</section>



</section>      <!--PAREO Functions-->

    <!--  1111111111111   -->


 </section>    <!--RAW Framework-->


    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->


<section anchor="archi" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The RAW Architecture</name>

<section anchor="model" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The RAW Conceptual Model</name>
    <t>
    RAW inherits the conceptual model described in section 4 of the DetNet
    Architecture <xref target="RFC8655"/>. RAW extends the DetNet service
    layer to provide additional agility against transmission loss.

    </t><t>

   A RAW Network Plane may be strict or loose, depending
   on whether RAW observes and takes actions on all hops or not. For instance,
   the packets between two wireless entities may be relayed over a wired
   infrastructure such as a Wi-Fi extended service set (ESS) or a 5G Core; in
   that case, RAW observes and control the transmission over the wireless first
   and last hops, as well as end-to-end metrics such as latency, jitter, and
   delivery ratio. This operation is loose since the structure and properties of
   the wired infrastructure are ignored, and may be either controlled by other
   means such as DetNet/TSN, or neglected in the face of the wireless hops.

    </t><t>
    A Controller Plane Function (CPF) called the
    Path Computation Element (PCE) <xref target="RFC4655"/> interacts with
    RAW Nodes over a Southbound API. The RAW Nodes are DetNet relays that are capable of additional diversity mechanisms and measurement functions related
    to the radio interface, in particular the PAREO diversity mechanisms.
    </t><t>
    The PCE defines a complex Track between an Ingress End System and an Egress
    End System, and indicates to the RAW Nodes where the PAREO operations may be actionned in the Network Plane. The Track may be expressed loosely to enable
    traversing a non-RAW subnetwork. In that case, the expectation is that the
    non-RAW subnetwork can be neglected in the RAW computation, that is,
    considered infinitely fast, reliable and/or available in comparison with the
    links between RAW nodes.
    </t>
<figure anchor="FigCPF">
          <name>RAW Nodes</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">


        CPF               CPF          CPF                 CPF


                       Southbound API
   _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-
 _-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-._-


                 RAW  --z   RAW  --z   RAW  --z   RAW
             z-- Node  z--  Node  z--  Node  z--  Node --z
  Ingress --z    /          /                           z-- Egress
  End           \          \         .. .                   End
  Node   ---z   /          /       .. ..  .             z-- Node
           z-- RAW  --z   RAW     ( non-RAW ) -- RAW --z
               Node  z--  Node --- ( Nodes  )   Node
                                      ... .
  --z   wireless           wired
   z--  link           --- link
</artwork>
</figure>

    <t>
    The Link-Layer metrics are reported to the PCE in a time-aggregated, e.g.,
    statistical fashion. Example Link-Layer metrics include typical Link
    bandwidth (the medium speed depends dynamically on the PHY mode and the
    number of users sharing the spectrum) and average and mean squared deviation
    of availability and reliability figures such as Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR)
    over long periods of time.
    </t><t>
    Based on those metrics, the PCE installs the Track with enough
    redundant forwarding solutions to ensure that the Network Plane can reliably
    deliver the packets within a System Level Agreement (SLA) associated to the
    flows that it transports.
    The SLA defines end-to-end reliability and availability requirements, where
    reliability may be expressed as a successful delivery in order and within a
    bounded delay of at least one copy of a packet.
    </t><t>
    Depending on the use case and the SLA, the Track may comprise non-RAW
    segments, either interleaved inside the Track, or all the way to
    the Egress End Node (e.g., a server in the Internet). RAW observes the
    Lower-Layer Links between RAW nodes (typically, radio links) and the
    end-to-end Network Layer operation to decide at all times which of the PAREO
    diversity schemes is actioned by which RAW Nodes.
    </t><t>
    Once a Track is established, per-segment and end-to-end reliability
    and availability statistics are periodically reported to the PCE to assure that
    the SLA can be met or have it recompute the Track if not.
    </t>

    </section> <!-- The RAW Conceptual Model -->

<section anchor="psepce" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>The Path Selection Engine</name>
 <t>
    RAW separates the path computation time scale at which a complex path is recomputed from the path selection time scale at which the forwarding decision is taken for one or a few packets (more in <xref target="timescale"/>).
    RAW operates at the path selection time scale.  The RAW problem is to decide, within the redundant solutions that are proposed by the PCE, which will be used for each packet to provide a Reliable and Available service while minimizing the waste of constrained resources.
    </t><t>
    To that effect, RAW defines the Path Selection Engine (PSE) that is the counter-part of the PCE to perform rapid local adjustments of the forwarding tables within the diversity that the PCE has selected for the Track.
    The PSE enables to exploit the richer forwarding capabilities with PAREO and scheduled transmissions at a faster time scale over the smaller domain that
    is the Track, in either a loose or a strict fashion.
    </t>
   <t>
        Compared to the PCE,
    the PSE operates on metrics that evolve faster, but that needs to be advertised at a fast rate but only locally, within the Track.
    The forwarding decision may also change rapidly, but wiht a scope that is
    also contained within the Track, with no visibility to the other Tracks and
    flows in the network. This is as opposed to the PCE that needs to observe
    the  whole network, and optimize all the Tracks globally, which can only be
    done at a slow pace and using long-term statistical metrics, as presented in
    <xref target="PCEPSEtable"/>.
    </t>
    <table anchor="PCEPSEtable"><name>PCE vs. PSE</name>
   <thead>
      <tr>
       <th> </th>
		   <th align='center'>PCE (Not in Scope)</th>
		   <th align='center'>PSE (In Scope)</th>
      </tr>

   </thead><tbody>

			<tr><td>Operation</td>
    			<td align='center'>Centralized</td>
    			<td align='center'>Source-Routed or Distributed</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Communication
</td>
    			<td align='center'>Slow, expensive</td>
    			<td align='center'>Fast, local</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Time Scale</td>
    			<td align='center'>hours and above</td>
    			<td align='center'>seconds and below</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Network Size</td>
    			<td align='center'>Large, many Tracks to optimize globally</td>
    			<td align='center'>Small, within one Track</td>
        </tr>


			<tr><td>Considered Metrics</td>
    			<td align='center'>Averaged, Statistical, Shade of grey</td>
    			<td align='center'>Instant values / boolean condition</td>
        </tr>



    </tbody>
    </table><t>
    The PSE sits in the DetNet Service sub-Layer of Edge and Relay Nodes. On the
    one hand, it operates on the packet flow, learning the Track and path
    selection information from the packet, possibly making local decision and
    retagging the packet to indicate so. On the other hand, the PSE interacts
    with the lower layers and with its peers to obtain up-to-date information
    about its radio links and the quality of the overall Track, respectively,
    as illustrated in <xref target="FigPSEcomp"/>.
    </t>

<figure anchor="FigPSEcomp">
          <name>PSE</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
            |
     packet | going
   down the | stack
 +==========v==========+=====================+=====================+
 |   (iOAM + iCTRL)    | (L2 Triggers, DLEP) |       (oOAM)        |
 +==========v==========+=====================+=====================+
 |     Learn from                                 Learn from       |
 |    packet tagging           Maintain           end-to-end       |
 +----------v----------+      Forwarding          OAM packets      |
 | Forwarding decision <        State        +---------^-----------|
 +----------v----------+                     |      Enrich or      |
 +    Retag Packet     |  Learn abstracted   >     Regenerate      |
 |    and Forward      | metrics about Links |     OAM packets     |
 +..........v..........+..........^..........+.........^.v.........+
 |                          Lower layers                           |
 +..........v.....................^....................^.v.........+
      frame | sent          Frame | L2 Ack        oOAM | | packet
       over | wireless        In  |                 In | | and out
            v                     |                    | v
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</section>
    <!--PCE vs. PSE-->

 <!--
<section anchor="stack" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>RAW Stack </name>
</section>
   RAW stack-->

<section anchor="aom" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>RAW OAM </name><t>
    RAW In-situ OAM operation in the Network Plane may observe either a full
    Track or subTracks that are being used at this time. Active RAW OAM may
    be needed to observe the unused segments and evaluate the desirability of
    a rerouting decision.
    Finally, the RAW Service Layer Assurance may observe the individual PAREO
    operation of a relay node to ensure that it is conforming; this might
    require injecting an OAM packet at an upstream point inside the Track and
    extracting that packet at another point downstream before it reaches the
    egress.
    </t><t>
    This observation feeds the RAW
    PSE that makes the decision on which PAREO function in actioned at which RAW
    Node, for one a small continuous series of packets.
     </t>
<figure anchor="Figranp2">
          <name>Observed Links in Radio Access Protection</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
<![CDATA[
                                   ...   ..
                RAN 1  -----  ...      ..  ...
             /              .    ..          ....
+-------+  /              .            ..      ....    +------+
|Ingress|-                .                     .....  |Egress|
|  End  |------ RAN 2 -- .       Internet       ....---| End  |
|System |-                ..                   .....   |System|
+-------+  \               .               ......      +------+
             \               ...   ...     .....
                RAN n  --------  ...   .....

       <------------------> <-------------------->
          Observed by OAM       Opaque to OAM

]]></artwork>
</figure><t>
    In the case of a End-to-End Protection in a Wireless Mesh, the Track is strict and congruent
    with the path so all links are observed. Conversely, in the case of Radio
    Access Protection, the Track is Loose and in that case only the first hop is observed; the rest of the path is abstracted and considered infinitely reliable.
    </t>
    <t>
    In the case of the Radio Access Protection, only the first hop is protected;
    the loss of a packet that was sent over one of the possible first hops is
    attributed to that first hop, even if a particular loss effectively happens
    farther down the path.
    </t>
    <t>
    The Links that are not observed by OAM are opaque to it, meaning that the
    OAM information is carried across and possibly echoed as data, but there is
    no information capture in intermediate nodes. In the example above, the
    Internet is opaque and not controlled by RAW; still the RAW OAM measures the
    end-to-end latency and delivery ratio for packets sent via each if RAN 1,
    RAN 2 and RAN 3, and determines whether a packet should be sent over either
    or a collection of those access links.
    </t>


<section anchor="dnoam" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>DetNet OAM</name>
 <t>
  <xref target="detnet" format="default"/> provides an OAM framework with
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework" format="default"/> that
  applies within the DetNet dataplane described in
  <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>,which is typically based on
  MPLS or IPv6 pseudowires.
  How the framework applies to IPv6 is detailed in
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-ip-oam" format="default"/>.
  Within that framework, OAM messages follow the same forward path as the data
  packets and gather information about their individual treatment at each hop.
  When the destination receives an OAM message, it gets a view on the full path
  or at least of a segment of the path from the source of the flow.
 </t>
 <t>
  In-situ OAM (IOAM) adds telemetry information about the experience of one
  packet within the packet itself
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-ippm-ioam-data" format="default"/>, with the caveats
  that the measurement and the consecutive update of the packet interfere with
  the operation being observed, e.g., may increase the latency of the packet
  for which it is measured and into which it is stamped.
 </t>
 <t>
  Note: IOAM and analogous on-path telemetry methods are capable of facilitating
  collection of useful telemetry information that characterizes the state of a
  system as experienced by the packet. But because of statistical character of a
  packet network, these methods may not be used to monitor the continuity of a
  path (Track) or proper connectivity of the Track (no leaking packets across
  Tracks).
 </t>
 <t>
  This effect can be alleviated by measuring on the fly but reporting later,
  e.g., by exporting the data as a separate management packet
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-ippm-ioam-direct-export" format="default"/>.
  <xref target="I-D.mirsky-ippm-hybrid-two-step" format="default"/> proposes an
  hybrid two-steps method (HTS) where a trigger message starts the measurement
  and a follow up along the Track packet gathers the measured data.
 </t>
 <t>
  <xref target="I-D.mirsky-ippm-epm" format="default">"Error Performance
  Measurement"</xref> uses Fault Management (FM) and Performance Management (PM)
  OAM mechanisms to determine availability/unavailability of a path according to
  predefined SLA.
 </t>
</section>
    <!--DetNet OAM-->

<section anchor="roam" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>RAW Extensions</name>

 <t>
 Classical OAM typically measures information at the transmitter, e.g.,
 residence time in the node or transmit queue size. With RAW, there is a need to
 combine information at the sender (number of retries) with that at the receiver
 (LQI, RSSI).
 This doubles the operating cost of an IAOM processing that would gather the
 experience of a single packet.
  </t>
 <t>
 The RAW PSE may be centralized at the Track Ingress, or distributed long the
 Track. Either way, the PSE needs instant information about the rest of the
 way to the destination over the possible next-hop adjacencies along the Track
 in order to decide how to perform simple forwarding, load balancing, and/or
 replication, as well as determining how much latency credit is available for
 ARQ.
  </t>
 <t>
 To provide that information timely, it makes sense that the OAM packets that
 gather instantaneous values from the radio senders and receivers at each hop
 flow on the reverse path and inform the PSE at the source and/or the PAREO
 relays about the state of the rest of the way. This is achieved using Reverse
 OAM packets that flow along the Reversed Track, West to East.
 </t>
 <t>
 Because the quality of transmission over a wireless medium varies continuously,
 it is important that RAW OAM captures the state of the medium across an adjacency
 over multiple transmission and over a recent period of time, whether the
 transmitted packets belong to this flow or another. Some of the measured information
 relates to the medium itself. In other words, the captured information does not
 only relate to the experience of one packet as is the case for IOAM, but also to the
 medium itself. This makes an approach like HTS more suitable as it can trigger
 the capture of multiple measurements over a short period of time. On the other
 hand, the PSE needs a continuous measurement stream where a single trigger
 is followed by a periodic follow up capture.
  </t>
 <t>
  In other words, the best suited OAM method to enable the PSE make accurate
  PAREO forwarding decisions is a periodic variation of the two-steps method
  flowing along the reverse Track, as a Reverse OAM technique.
 <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-oam-support" format="default"/> provides more
 information on the RAW OAM problem and solution approaches.
 </t>
</section>
    <!--DetNet OAM-->

<section anchor="oametrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
 <name>Observed Metrics</name>
 <t>
 The Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP)
 <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> from
 <xref target="MANET" format="default"/> can be leveraged at each hop
 to derive generic radio metrics (e.g., based on LQI, RSSI, queueing delays
 and ETX) on individual hops.
 </t>
 <t>
 Those lower-layer metrics are aggregated along a multihop segment into abstract
 layer 3 information that reflect the instant reliability and latency of the
 observed path.
 </t>
</section>
    <!--Observed Metrics -->




</section>
    <!--RAW OAM-->
<section anchor="flowid" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>Flow Identification vs. Path Identification</name>

<t>
    Section 4.7 of the DetNet Architecture <xref target="RFC8655"/> ties the
    app-flow identification which is an appliation layer concept with the
    network path identification that depends on the networking technology by
    "exporting of flow identification", e.g., to a MPLS label.
</t><t>
    With RAW, this exporting operation is injective but not bijective.
    e.g., a flow is fully placed within one RAW Track, but not all packets along
    that Track are necessarily part of the same flow. For instance, out-of-band
    OAM packets must circulate in the exact same fashion as the flows that they
    observe. It results that the flow identification that maps to to app-flow
    at the network layer must be separate from the path identification that is
    used to forward a packet.
</t><t>

    Section 3.4 of the DetNet data-plane framework <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/> indicates that for
    a DetNet IP Data Plane, a flow is identified by an IPv6 6-tuple.
    With RAW, that 6-tuple is not what indicates the Track, in other words, the
    flow ID is not the Track ID.
</t><t>
    For instance, the 6TiSCH Architecture
    <xref target="RFC9030" format="default"/>
    uses a combination of the address of the Egress End System and an instance
    identifier in a Hop-by-hop option to indicate a Track. This way, if a packet
    "escapes" the Track, it will reach the Track Egress point through normal
    routing and be treated at the service layer through, say, elimination and
    reordering.
</t><t>
    The RAW service includes forwarding over a subset of the Links that form the
    Track (a subTrack). Packets from the same or a different flow that are routed through the same Track will not necessarily traverse the same Links. The PSE
    selects a subTrack for a packet based on the links
    that are preferred and those that should be avoided at this time.
</t><t>
    Each packet is forwarded within the subTrack that provides the best
    adequation with the SLA of the flow and the energy and bandwidth constraints
    of the network.
</t>

<figure anchor="Figflowvstrack">
          <name>Flow Injection</name>
       <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt="">
<![CDATA[

            Flow 1 (6-tuple) ----+
                                 |
       Flow 2 (6-tuple)  ---+    |
                            |    |
    OAM     -----------+    |    |
                       |    |    |
                       |    |    |
                  |    |    |    |    |
                  |    v    v    v    |
                  |                   |
                  +---------+---------+
                            |
                            |
     Track i (Ingress IP Address, RPLinstanceId)
                            |
                            |
                            |
            +---------+-----+--....-------+
            |         |                   |
            |         |                   |
     subTrack 1    subTrack 2          subTrack n
            |         |                   |
            |         |                   |
            V         V                   V
         +-----------------------------------+
         |                                   |
         |         Destination               |
         |                                   |
         +-----------------------------------+


]]>
       </artwork>
</figure>
<t>
    With 6TiSCH,
    packets are tagged with the same (destination address, instance ID)
    will experience the same RAW service regardless of the IPv6 6-tuple
    that indicates the flow. The forwarding does not depend on whether the
    packets transport application flows or OAM. In the generic
    case, the Track or the subTrack can be signaled in the packet through other
    means, e.g., encoded in the suffix of the destination address as a Segment
    Routing Service Instruction <xref target="RFC8402"/>, or leveraging Bit
    Index Explicit Replication <xref target="RFC8279"/> Traffic Engineering
     <xref target="I-D.ietf-bier-te-arch"/>.
</t>
</section>
    <!--Flow Identification vs. Path Identification-->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Source-Routed vs. Distributed Forwarding Decision</name>
      <t>
   Within a large routed topology, the route-over mesh operation builds a
   particular complex Track with one source and one or more destinations; within
   the Track,
   packets may follow different paths and may be subject to RAW forwarding
   operations that include replication, elimination, retries, overhearing and
   reordering.
      </t>
      <t>
    The RAW forwarding decisions include the selection of points of replication
   and elimination, how many retries can take place, and a limit of validity for
    the packet beyond which the packet should be destroyed rather than forwarded
    uselessly further down the Track.
      </t>
      <t>
    The decision to apply the RAW techniques must be done quickly, and depends on
    a very recent and precise knowledge of the forwarding conditions within the
    complex Track. There is a need for an observation method to provide the RAW
    Data Plane with the specific knowledge of the state of the Track for
    the type of flow of interest (e.g., for a QoS level of interest). To observe
    the whole Track in quasi real time, RAW considers existing tools such as
    L2-triggers, DLEP, BFD and leverages in-band and out-of-band OAM to capture
    and report that information to the PSE.
      </t>
      <t>
   One possible way of making the RAW forwarding decisions within a Track is to
   position a unique PSE at the Ingress and express its decision in-band in the packet, which requires the explicit signaling of the subTrack within the
   Track. In that case, the RAW forwarding operation along the Track is encoded
   by the source, e.g., by indicating the subTrack in the Segment Routing (SRv6)
   Service Instruction, or by leveraging BIER-TE such as done with
   <xref target="I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
    The alternate way is to operate the PSE in each forwarding Node, which makes
    the RAW forwarding decisions for a packet on its own, based on its knowledge
    of the expectation (timeliness and reliability) for that packet and a recent
    observation of the rest of the way across the possible paths based on OAM.
    Information about the desired service should be placed in the packet and
    matched with the forwarding Node's capabilities and policies.
      </t>
      <t>
    In either case, a per-track/subTrack state is installed in all the
    intermediate Nodes to recognize the packets that are following a Track and
    determine the forwarding operation to be applied.
      </t>

    </section>
    <!-- Track Source-Routed vs. Distributed RAW Decision -->


    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Encapsulation and Decapsulation</name>
 <t>
    In the generic case where the Track Ingress Node is not the source of the
    Packet, the Ingress Node needs to encapsulate IP-in-IP to ensure that the
    Destination IP Address is that of the Egress Node and that the necessary
    Headers (Routing Header, Segment Routing Header and/or Hop-By-Hop Header)
    can be added to the packet to signal the Track or the subTrack, conforming
    <xref target="RFC8200"/> that discourages the insertion of a Header on the
    fly.
 </t><t>
    In the specific case where the Ingress Node is the source of the packet, the
    encapsulation can be avoided, provided that the source adds the necessary
    headers and that the destination is set to the Egress Node. Forwarding
    to a final destination beyond the Egress Node is possible, e.g., with a
    Segment Routing Header that signals the rest of the way. In that case
    a Hop-by-Hop Header is not recommmended since its validity is within the
    Track only.
 </t><t>
 </t>

</section>
    <!--Encapsulation and Decapsulation -->

    <!--  11111111111111111111    -->
</section>
    <!--RAW Architecture -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->



    <section anchor="SecurityConsiderations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
    <t>
    RAW uses all forms of diversity including radio technology and physical path
    to increase the reliability and availability in the face of unpredictable
    conditions. While this is not done specifically to defeat an attacker, the
    amount of diversity used in RAW makes an attack harder to achieve.
    </t>




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Forced Access</name>
    <t>
    RAW will typically select the cheapest collection of links that matches the
    requested SLA, for instance, leverage free WI-Fi vs. paid 3GPP access. By
    defeating the cheap connectivity (e.g., PHY-layer interference) the attacker
    can force an End System to use the paid access and increase the cost of the
    transmission for the user.
    </t>

      </section><!-- Forced Access -->

    <!--  111111111111111111111    -->
    </section>
      <!--Security Considerations-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->




    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>
      <!--IANA Considerations-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>The editor wishes to thank:
      </t>
      <dl>
    <dt>Xavi Vilajosana:</dt><dd>Wireless Networks Research Lab, Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</dd>
    <dt>Remous-Aris Koutsiamanis:</dt><dd>IMT Atlantique</dd>
    <dt>Nicolas Montavont:</dt><dd>IMT Atlantique</dd>
    <dt>Rex Buddenberg:</dt><dd>Individual contributor</dd>
    <dt>Greg Mirsky:</dt><dd>ZTE</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>for their contributions to the text and ideas exposed in this document.
      </t>
    </section>
      <!--ConTributors-->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->

   <section><name>Acknowledgments</name>
   <t>TBD
   </t>
   </section>
   <!-- Acknowledgments -->
    <!--  000000000000000000000    -->


  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference   target="I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless"     to="IPoWIRELESS"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-raw-technologies"   to="RAW-TECHNOS"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-raw-oam-support"     to="RAW-OAM"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.farkas-raw-5g"        to="RAW-5G"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases"   to="RAW-USE-CASES"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination" to="BIER-PREF"/>
<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-detnet-ip-oam"   to="DetNet-IP-OAM"/>

<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework"     to="DetNet-OAM"/>


<displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-bier-te-arch"    to="BIER-TE"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC3272"                  to="TE"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC5880"                  to="BFD"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC3411"                  to="STD 62"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC7490"                  to="RLFA-FRR"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC5714"                  to="FRR"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8402"                  to="SR-ARCHI"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8200"                  to="IPv6"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8279"                  to="BIER"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC8938"                  to="DetNet-DP"/>
<displayreference   target="RFC9030"                  to="6TiSCH-ARCHI"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
    <name>Normative References</name>


<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9030.xml"/>
<!-- 6TiSCH Architecture -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-technologies.xml"/>
<!-- Reliable and Available Wireless Technologies -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-use-cases.xml"/>
<!-- RAW use cases -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
<!-- PCE -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5880.xml"/>
<!-- Bidirectional Forwarding Detection  -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6291.xml"/>
<!-- Guidelines for the Use of the "OAM" Acronym in the IETF  -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8578.xml"/>
<!-- Deterministic Networking Use Cases -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml"/>
<!-- IPv6 -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
<!-- Segment Routing Architecture -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8279.xml"/>
<!-- BIER -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8175.xml"/>
<!-- Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8557.xml"/>
<!-- DetNet problem statement -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml"/>
<!-- Deterministic Networking Architecture -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9049.xml"/>
<!-- Path Aware Networking: Obstacles to Deployment  -->

      </references>
    <!--Normative References-->


      <references>
    <name>Informative References</name>


<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml"/>
<!-- IP -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3272.xml"/>
<!-- TE -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml"/>
<!-- An Architecture for Describing Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4090.xml"/>
<!-- Fast Reroute Extensions to RSVP-TE -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5714.xml"/>
<!--  IP Fast Reroute Framework -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7490.xml"/>
<!--   Remote Loop-Free Alternate (LFA) Fast Reroute (FRR) -->

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8938.xml"/>
<!--   Deterministic Networking (DetNet) Data Plane Framework -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.thubert-bier-replication-elimination.xml"/>
<!-- BIER-TE extensions for Packet Replication and Elimination Function (PREF) and OAM -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-ip-oam.xml"/>
<!-- Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) for Deterministic Networks (detnet) with IP Data Plane -->


<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.farkas-raw-5g.xml"/>
<!-- RAW 5G-->


<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-bier-te-arch.xml"/>
<!-- Traffic Engineering for Bit Index Explicit Replication (BIER-TE)-->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.thubert-6man-ipv6-over-wireless.xml"/>
<!-- IPv6 Neighbor Discovery on Wireless Networks -->

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-raw-oam-support.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ippm-ioam-direct-export.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-oam-framework.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mirsky-ippm-hybrid-two-step.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mirsky-ippm-epm.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mirsky-bfd-mpls-demand.xml"/>
<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ippm-ioam-data.xml"/>

    <reference anchor="NASA" target="https://kscddms.ksc.nasa.gov/Reliability/Documents/150814-3bWhatIsReliability.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>RELIABILITY: Definition &amp; Quantitative Illustration</title>
        <author  initials="T." surname="Adams" fullname="Tim Adams" >
          <organization>NASA</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="MANET" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-manet/">
      <front>
        <title> Mobile Ad hoc Networking</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="detnet" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-detnet/">
      <front>
        <title>Deterministic Networking</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="SPRING" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-spring/">
      <front>
        <title>Source Packet Routing in Networking</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="BIER" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-bier/">
      <front>
        <title>Bit Indexed Explicit Replication</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    <!--
    <reference anchor="TEAS" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-teas/">
      <front>
        <title>Traffic Engineering Architecture and Signaling</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    -->
    <!--
    <reference anchor="PCE" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-pce/">
      <front>
        <title>Path Computation Element</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    -->
    <reference anchor="BFD" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-bfd/">
      <front>
        <title>Bidirectional Forwarding Detection</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="CCAMP" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-ccamp/">
      <front>
        <title>Common Control and Measurement Plane</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="IPPM" target="https://dataTracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-ippm/">
      <front>
        <title>IP Performance Measurement</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
      </references>
    <!--Informative References-->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
